<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://perrotta.dev/rss.xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Legacy on ¬ just serendipity 🍀</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/</link><description>Recent content in Legacy on ¬ just serendipity 🍀</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</managingEditor><webMaster>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</webMaster><copyright>© 2013 - 2026 Thiago Perrotta ·
[some rights reserved](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/) ·
a fork of [hugo ʕ•ᴥ•ʔ bear](https://github.com/janraasch/hugo-bearblog/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 01:11:24 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Arch Linux on macbook installation notes</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2017/02/arch-linux-on-macbook-installation-notes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 18:36:02 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2017/02/arch-linux-on-macbook-installation-notes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Imported from &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/thiagowfx/"&gt;thiagowfx&lt;/a&gt;@&amp;rsquo;s gist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arch Linux Installation Notes (Macbook, UEFI, LVM ON LUKS, swap, btrfs root and home):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create an installation disk (USB Flash Drive):
&lt;a href="http://zanshin.net/2015/02/05/arch-linux-on-a-macbook-pro-part-1-creating-a-usb-installer/"&gt;http://zanshin.net/2015/02/05/arch-linux-on-a-macbook-pro-part-1-creating-a-usb-installer/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partitioning (EFI boot partition + LVM on LUKS partition):
&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/jasonwryan/4618490"&gt;https://gist.github.com/jasonwryan/4618490&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naming conventions:
&lt;a href="http://www.pavelkogan.com/2014/05/23/luks-full-disk-encryption/"&gt;http://www.pavelkogan.com/2014/05/23/luks-full-disk-encryption/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support docs:
&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Dm-crypt/Encrypting_an_entire_system#LVM_on_LUKS"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Dm-crypt/Encrypting_an_entire_system#LVM_on_LUKS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bootloader: &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/systemd-boot"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/systemd-boot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Official Installation Guide:
&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Installation_guide"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Installation_guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="post-installation"&gt;Post-installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Mac#Arch_Linux_only"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Mac#Arch_Linux_only&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/yantis/instant-archlinux-on-mac"&gt;https://github.com/yantis/instant-archlinux-on-mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Arch Linux on macbook installation notes"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Linux goodness in your Chromebook</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2016/09/linux-goodness-in-your-chromebook/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 16:29:07 -0200</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2016/09/linux-goodness-in-your-chromebook/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.google.com.br/chromebook/"&gt;Chromebooks&lt;/a&gt; are excellent for testing
and playing with Linux userland[1] stuff. And, even better, (almost) every
change you make to it can be reset back to its factory state — even in the worst
case of completely wiping ChromeOS from your computer. As long as you don&amp;rsquo;t mess
up with its &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Firmware"&gt;firmware&lt;/a&gt;, you can do
whatever you want and still be safe. Most models are cheap, battery life is
amazing for a cheap Linux laptop (8+ hours, depending on the device and on
usage)[2], Linux support is great (well, it ships with a Linux OS, right?) —
even for most touchscreen models [citation needed] — and it is simple (as in
KISS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the previous paragraph sounded a little repetitive, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to focus
on two of my previous points here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can do whatever you want and still remain safe.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Indeed, you can
reset your chromebook to its factory state with just a few clicks — this is
still hard to do with Windows and OS X, as far as I know. I think Windows 10
is introducing a feature to ease this process, however I am not sure about it
yet. This is super important (and convenient!) for people playing with a
ChromeOS device — like me. My usual way to reset the system back to &amp;ldquo;factory
state&amp;rdquo; was, usually, to install a Linux distro with the btrfs filesystem so I
could create a snapshot upon the installation was finished, and then revert
back to it at anytime I wanted. However, this solution is a little
cumbersome. The second usual solution would be to simply use a virtual
machine, but I don&amp;rsquo;t need to reiterate that this is slow and limited in many
ways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple&lt;/strong&gt;. This is really important if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to have headaches in
the long run. For starters, simplicity is always a trade-off that involves
performance: it is hard to be simple with a core i7 CPU, so if you choose the
KISS path, you are deliberately sacrificing some of your performance. Once
you accept that, we can move forward: Chromebooks are very simple devices.
They&amp;rsquo;re almost directly comparable to a tablet with a keyboard. Sometimes
they feel like a full-featured arduino.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were some small highlights about my decision to get one. Now here&amp;rsquo;s the
good stuff:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="there-be-dragons"&gt;There be dragons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer/Warning&lt;/strong&gt;: these will potentially void the warranty of your device,
and they are only recommended if you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing. Be a good user and
research before messing up with your system. I will provide upstream links with
documentation as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/poking-around-your-chrome-os-device"&gt;Enable developer
mode&lt;/a&gt;
— it&amp;rsquo;s a must; however, it weakens the security of your device. Beware and
research! This can be totally reverted with a single keystroke (SPACE) at the
login screen that will appear in every subsequent boot of your system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/how-tos-and-troubleshooting/install-software-on-base-images"&gt;dev_install&lt;/a&gt;
— to get fdisk, python, tmux, nano, emerge (for binaries), and so on. These
are just a few developer tools, they won&amp;rsquo;t scale and you won&amp;rsquo;t get whatever
package you want in your vanilla ChromeOS, however these might help a lot with
simple tasks. For example, you can format a SD card or an USB Flash Drive
directly from ChromeOS upon running this tool — otherwise, you&amp;rsquo;d usually have
to use another computer, with another OS to do it. It uses just a little space
(~100M+ or so), and it can be totally reverted with &lt;code&gt;devinstall --uninstall&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to the &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/chromebook/answer/1086915?hl=en"&gt;beta
channel&lt;/a&gt; if you
want to be slightly more into the bleeding edge — but not too much as in the
dev channel. In fact, at the time of this post, select devices in beta channel
have support for Android apps in ChromeOS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a new shell (crosh) with Ctrl + Alt + T. The default username is
&amp;lsquo;chronos&amp;rsquo;, without any password.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User-writable locations are: /usr/local (in particular, /usr/local/bin is in
your PATH env variable out-of-the-box (echo $PATH)), /tmp and
/home/chronos/user/Downloads. There might be more, but these are enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can also insert removable media (USB flash drives, SD cards), which would
show up on /media. ChromeOS can read/write filesystems formatted as ext{2,3,4}
and FAT{,32} at least.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the basics. However, you will soon find out that you cannot do too
much with ChromeOS, even with these modifications. In this case, there are three
options, and all of them involve getting a Linux distribution in some way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(RECOMMENDED)&lt;/strong&gt; Install a Linux distro on either a SD card or an USB Flash
Drive and dual-boot from it. It is really easy to dual-boot, you just press
C-d to boot from the internal eMMC / SSD, or C-u to boot from external
storage. There&amp;rsquo;s no need to play with grub, EFI, or any (other) fancy
bootloader. If you change your mind later on, just format your SD card: there
is no need to change anything on ChromeOS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(NOT RECOMMENDED BY ME)&lt;/strong&gt; Completely wipe ChromeOS by installing another
Linux distribution on its place. Although it&amp;rsquo;s easy to revert this process
through &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/chromebook/answer/1080595"&gt;recovery
media&lt;/a&gt;, it completely
defeats the purpose of getting a Chromebook in the first place, especially
now that Android apps are starting to become available on them (for
touchscreen devices, of course).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(PROBABLY WOULDN&amp;rsquo;T RECOMMEND, BUT YOU MAY LIKE IT)&lt;/strong&gt; Install a chroot
alongside your ChromeOS, such as
&lt;a href="https://github.com/dnschneid/crouton"&gt;crouton&lt;/a&gt;. I tried it however I hated
it. It is very buggy and opinionated, somewhat similar to oh-my-zsh: both of
them promise to deliver a good framework and they&amp;rsquo;re kinda large open source
projects, however they do lots of automatic things for you, and you end up
not knowing what is happening to your system. It opposes the Arch Linux
philosophy, being user-friendly rather than user-centered. Some people like
it, I won&amp;rsquo;t argue this, it can work for them; but not for me. An alternative
would be to install a chroot manually, without the help of crouton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen the first option, installing Arch Linux ARM on my Chromebook. So
far, so good: it&amp;rsquo;s working very well. Storage is easily shared between the two
OSes (by using the SD card). There&amp;rsquo;s more to get out of my system, and I intend
to share new findings in this blog. &lt;strong&gt;In particular, the most important one: to
find an easy way (not crouton!) of running whatever Linux-compatible application
I want from within Chrome OS, without dual-booting.&lt;/strong&gt; I have a few ideas (well,
it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of creating a KISS chroot), I just want to polish them a
little more before trying them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="see-also"&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://imgur.com/BrVVyNi"&gt;Generic Chrome OS Troubleshooter Chart v0.3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t say the same for kernel stuff though. It is not trivial to install
a bootloader (such as grub) or to boot a custom kernel in a Chromebook. It&amp;rsquo;s
possible indeed, it&amp;rsquo;s just not as nice or as easy as an average PC or Mac
laptop from today, especially if you have the intention of keeping the
upstream OS (Chrome OS) in the device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People probably would cite a Macbook, a Surface Pro, or something else
similar here. For starters, did you see how much they cost, in comparison to
an average Chromebook? Such a comparison wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be fair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Linux goodness in your Chromebook"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Installing Haiku from an existing linux</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2015 17:20:19 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what8217s-haiku-in-the-first-place"&gt;What’s Haiku in the first place?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an operating system, period. What might cause a small surprise is that it is not based either on Linux or on BSD — and yet it is (probably) runnable in your modern computer/laptop!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I most like on it is that the system is integrated with the GUI, so the end user gets a nice experience. This is not so common as it sounds: most Linux distributions are simply a collection of programs and utilities put together in one place, but they are not necessarily integrated — however, &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; can integrate them. This makes all the difference between user-friendly and user-centered paradigms&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Haiku is simple, so for me this post is more a hobby than something useful that I will use in the future; however, I find that knowing about more and more about different operating systems has its own advantages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more, see &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/about"&gt;https://www.haiku-os.org/about&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="installing-haiku"&gt;Installing Haiku&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; most of those instructions come from &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/guides/installing_haiku_image_disk_partition"&gt;the Haiku installation guide&lt;/a&gt;. Also, thanks David Couzelis for kindly giving me some advice and pointing me out to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get Haiku. You can do it either from &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/get-haiku"&gt;the official download page&lt;/a&gt;, or get nightly releases from &lt;a href="http://download.haiku-os.org/nightly-images/x86_gcc2_hybrid/"&gt;the nightly builds page&lt;/a&gt;. I personally recommend the nightly releases; I first installed the latest non-nightly one, but later on I discovered that is was very old (circa 2012): it didn’t even have a package manager.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which image should you download? In this post, I am assuming we’ll install Haiku directly to a (real) disk, so I’m downloading the &lt;strong&gt;raw&lt;/strong&gt; image. Actually, the &lt;strong&gt;anyboot&lt;/strong&gt; image can also be downloaded — and this is the one you will get if you opted for a non-nightly version; however, the anyboot image will be converted to a raw one in step 3 before we proceed. So, skip the next step if you downloaded the raw image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got your anyboot image? Now, convert it to raw (run this from a bash compatible shell):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ dd if=haiku-anyboot.image of=haiku.raw bs=1M skip=$(expr $(od -j 454 -N4 -i -A n haiku-anyboot.image) / 2048)
$ dd if=/dev/zero of=haiku.raw bs=1 seek=506 count=4 conv=notrunc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (2022)&lt;/strong&gt;: These days &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; supports &lt;code&gt;status=progress&lt;/code&gt; to display the image writing progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now that we got a raw image, we are writing it directly to a disk partition. First things first: find 3GB or more of free space in your disk. Then create room for a partition in there (for example, with &lt;em&gt;fdisk&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;gparted)&lt;/em&gt;. Got it? Now create a partition in there. I’ll assume the partition is &lt;code&gt;/dev/sda42&lt;/code&gt;. Please change 42 for the appropriate number in your case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the raw image to the partition (this should be done as ROOT); &lt;strong&gt;WARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: double check the partition and the disk number, otherwise you might lose data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ dd if=haiku.raw of=/dev/sda42 bs=1M conv=notrunc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol start="6"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the installation &lt;em&gt;bootable&lt;/em&gt;: you’ll need to compile and run the &lt;em&gt;makebootabletiny&lt;/em&gt; program, which can be downloaded from &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/guides/installing_haiku_image_disk_partition"&gt;the Haiku installation guide&lt;/a&gt;. It is a simple C program, so:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ gcc makebootabletiny.c -o makebootabletiny
% ./makebootabletiny /dev/sda42 # this one: as ROOT&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol start="7"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make your bootloader know about Haiku. If you’re using &lt;code&gt;grub2&lt;/code&gt;z, you can add something such as the following lines to &lt;code&gt;/etc/grub.d/40_custom&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;menuentry &amp;#34;Haiku OS&amp;#34; {
 set root(hd0,42)
 chainloader &amp;#43;1
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol start="8"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then run as root: &lt;em&gt;grub-mkconfig -o /boot/grub/grub.cfg&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Done!&lt;/strong&gt; Now you should be able to boot into Haiku.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="now-what"&gt;Now what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is not a review of Haiku, so I’m stopping here. However, if I write a review about Haiku, I’ll do that from Haiku 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m just leaving this here: &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/slideshows/haiku-1"&gt;https://www.haiku-os.org/slideshows/haiku-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, Arch Linux is user-centered, which means that you’re supposed to integrate the system as you wish. If you don’t wish that then you’re screwed anyway, so go away 🙂&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Installing Haiku from an existing linux"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Recording screencasts on Linux</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/recording-screencasts-on-linux/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2015 21:03:48 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/recording-screencasts-on-linux/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One-line self-documenting functions, put this into your shell init file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;# ffmpeg x11 screencasting
# it will just record video: no audio
# dimensions of your screen are automatically calculated
_ffmpeg-screencast() {
 ffmpeg -f x11grab -s $(xdpyinfo | awk &amp;#39;/dimensions:/ {print $2}&amp;#39;) -r 25 -i :0.0 -qscale 0 $HOME/ffmpeg-out-$(date &amp;#39;&amp;#43;%Y-%m-%d-%H-%M-%S&amp;#39;).mkv
}

# ffmpeg x11 screencasting with audio
# it supersedes the previous function
# source of the audio is determined with `pavucontrol`: open it then go to the &amp;#34;recording&amp;#34; tab. You can select between the microphone or your computer as audio sources
_ffmpeg-screencast-audio() {
 ffmpeg -f alsa -i pulse -acodec pcm_s16le -f x11grab -s $(xdpyinfo | awk &amp;#39;/dimensions:/ {print $2}&amp;#39;) -r 25 -i :0.0 -qscale 0 $HOME/ffmpeg-out-$(date &amp;#39;&amp;#43;%Y-%m-%d-%H-%M-%S&amp;#39;).mkv
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="observations"&gt;Observations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to get this automatically, you might be interested in my
dotfiles repo. In particular, inspect the .alias file, where those functions
are located (at least at the time of this post; things change).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio recording works best with Pulse Audio (citation needed). I haven&amp;rsquo;t
tested with alsa only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pavucontrol is just a fancy interface for configuring pulseaudio, but there
are others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tweak those parameters&amp;hellip;ffmpeg is a really powerful tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I tested this on the i3 window manager, and it works beautifully. I tested
some GUI screencasting programs on it before and the results were poor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source of this script: a merge of several ones on the web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh yes, and you can stop the screen capturing with the &amp;lsquo;q&amp;rsquo; key or with a
classical Control-C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; thanks Victor for a small improvement with &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; in the above
functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Recording screencasts on Linux"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Running Ogre3d locally (without installing it)</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/running-ogre3d-locally-without-installing-it/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 03:05:25 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/running-ogre3d-locally-without-installing-it/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://thiagoperrotta.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/11056835_726102464175254_2082355176_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://thiagoperrotta.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/11056835_726102464175254_2082355176_n.jpg?w=300" alt="simple build systems, huh?"
 loading="lazy" decoding="async" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; simple build systems, huh? Hello there. In this post we will run the &amp;ldquo;Basic 1&amp;rdquo; example from the &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php"&gt;Ogre3d wiki&lt;/a&gt; without installing &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/"&gt;ogre&lt;/a&gt; in the system. For that, I&amp;rsquo;ll assume you&amp;rsquo;re using a *nix system. First things first: grab the latest ogre version. At the time of this post, it is the 1.9 release, and you can find its repository &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/sinbad/ogre/downloads"&gt;on Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; you want to download the 1.9 version using the tag download feature from Bitbucket; &lt;strong&gt;do not&lt;/strong&gt; simply download the master branch. After that, extract it, create a build directory inside its directory, cd into it, and do a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cmake .. -DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=$HOME/.lib -DOGRE_INSTALL_SAMPLES=TRUE -DOGRE_INSTALL_DOCS=TRUE -DOGRE_INSTALL_SAMPLES_SOURCE=TRUE -DCMAKE_BUILD_TYPE=Release
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty much standard cmake build. If your system is missing some of its dependencies, you will be warned and you should install them. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;make OgreDoc install
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it is a good moment to read &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/303/"&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt;. The usual difference here is that we don&amp;rsquo;t do a normal &lt;strong&gt;make install&lt;/strong&gt;. Why? Because we don&amp;rsquo;t want our stuff ending up on &lt;strong&gt;/usr/local.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead, we want it somewhere where we have full access as a normal (non-root) user &amp;ndash; in this example, &lt;strong&gt;$HOME/.lib/ogre&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="basic-1"&gt;Basic 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, head to the &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php?page=Basic&amp;#43;Tutorial&amp;#43;1"&gt;basic 1&lt;/a&gt; page of the ogre wiki and download its example. You should try to build it, but take care to change all ogre3d references from /usr/local to your new install directory ($HOME/.lib/ogre). Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s it. &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; if the &lt;em&gt;basic 1&lt;/em&gt; download doesn&amp;rsquo;t come with a CMakeLists.txt file, you can download it from &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php?page=Building&amp;#43;Your&amp;#43;Projects&amp;#43;With&amp;#43;CMake"&gt;the Ogre CMake wiki page&lt;/a&gt; (clean ogre cmake project). You can use it verbatim; just put it in the same directory as the basic 1 files &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; -- again &amp;ndash; change any references to &lt;em&gt;/usr/local&lt;/em&gt; to your new install directory. Also, copy the &lt;strong&gt;dist/&lt;/strong&gt; directory too (if it is missing from the Basic 1 project), I&amp;rsquo;ll add a small observation: in the case cmake complains about pkg-config, try adding this line to the top of your CMakeLists.txt (but after the project version):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;set(ENV{PKG_CONFIG_PATH} &amp;quot;$ENV{HOME}/.lib/ogre/lib/pkgconfig:$ENV{PKG_CONFIG_PATH}&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credits:&lt;/strong&gt; the build style I adopted here was derived from the &lt;a href="https://projects.archlinux.org/svntogit/community.git/tree/trunk/PKGBUILD?h=packages/ogre"&gt;Ogre Arch Linux package.&lt;/a&gt; Thanks Sven for your excellent packaging skills! :) &lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; in your &lt;em&gt;plugins.cfg&lt;/em&gt; , &lt;strong&gt;do not&lt;/strong&gt; use &amp;ldquo;$HOME&amp;rdquo; as your PluginFolder. This seems to cause issues when you run your ogre app. Instead, expand $HOME manually (in my case, to &amp;lsquo;/home/thiago&amp;rsquo;). This is not much portable, I know, but there must be some workaround for this I haven&amp;rsquo;t discovered yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image credit: a screenshot from the &amp;ldquo;Clean Code&amp;rdquo; software engineering book by Robert C. Martin (a good one, by the way).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Running Ogre3d locally (without installing it)"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Documented dotfiles</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/documented-dotfiles/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 04:06:31 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/documented-dotfiles/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I just documented my dotfiles to make them easier to understand. &lt;a href="https://github.com/thiagowfx/dotfiles"&gt;Check them out on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Documented dotfiles"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Instagram</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/thoughts-on-instagram/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 05:18:09 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>serenity</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/thoughts-on-instagram/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; this is a brief article which exposes my opinion about a free web
service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time I refrained myself from creating an Instagram account for some
reasons. Those reasons are not much different for the delayed birth of my
Facebook profile. Let&amp;rsquo;s talk a little about them and discuss if they were or not
valid:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A. Too mainstream&lt;/strong&gt;: yeah, Instagram is pop. One of the top downloads of
smartphones app stores nowadays. So what, you just stop using a service just
because it is mainstream, and period? No, no, no. But&amp;hellip;for every mainstream
service, caution is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A.1 Privacy&lt;/strong&gt;: Most accounts from people I currently follow on Instagram are
public by default (neverthless, this is the default setting of Instagram). Not
cool, dude, not cool. This is a short essay and you probably know what I would
talk here, so let&amp;rsquo;s be &lt;strong&gt;brief&lt;/strong&gt; : most of those people are either not concerned
or don&amp;rsquo;t know what the problem of this deliberate practice might cause them a
day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A.2 Did you read its terms of service?&lt;/strong&gt; Photos are stored forever in there
(in principle), even after you delete them. And what one person &amp;ndash; for example,
either a complete stranger or the company behind Instagram itself &amp;ndash; could to
with them? So many things. The most common underrated example is: selling them
&amp;ndash; plus information associated with them &amp;ndash; to other companies, so they can (for
example) better target ads to you. This is not simply a matter of ads: it also
creates a bigger and bigger bubblein which you get stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m just posting random photos in there, so I don&amp;rsquo;t care. But hey, look at other
people profiles. They post photos about themselves all the time. $$$$oooooo many
data&amp;hellip;one more thing, remember: Instagram was created exactly for this purpose:
you are encouraged to use it just from your phone (not from the web), and there
is a big &amp;ldquo;shoot photo&amp;rdquo; button. While you can upload photos to it manually
(instead of shooting and submitting them there directly), this is not encouraged
&lt;strong&gt;by design&lt;/strong&gt;. So hey, a big database of public photos of Bob and Alice,
available 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember&lt;/strong&gt;: when the service is free, &lt;strong&gt;YOU&lt;/strong&gt; are the product (author needed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is maintreamness a problem? That depends on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**B.**A social network &lt;strong&gt;represents&lt;/strong&gt; what &lt;strong&gt;most&lt;/strong&gt; of its users make from it.
And&amp;hellip;what most (I repeat: most) users use Instagram for? For &lt;strong&gt;bragging&lt;/strong&gt;.
That&amp;rsquo;s it. You might try to argue it is different, but it is not. One could say
this is human nature, but if it is, then I find it pretty sad. I always had this
suspicion, but only after creating an Instagram account I could confirm it. So
what? Pretty simple: I&amp;rsquo;ll just delete the app from my smartphone. I won&amp;rsquo;t delete
my account because I may need it in the future (don&amp;rsquo;t forget: people post data;
data might become valuable anytime later on). However, if you find bragging cool
(I&amp;rsquo;m not judging, just stating that I don&amp;rsquo;t like this), then Instagram is
probably the perfect social network for you. It is even better than Facebook
(actually, it supersedes it; you can automatically make every new photo of yours
appear on Facebook automatically, yay!) in this sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C. Design&lt;/strong&gt;: despite the previous item, I have to say something: I appreciate
the engineering and the design of the service. Engineering? Well, I previously
said the service is consumed by many people, millions of them, and yet it has a
very good response time. Design? Yeah, the app and the service are very well
written and conceived. UX is amazing, the app is pretty much intuitive and easy
for newcomers to learn it. And it follows the Unix philosophy as a bonus: &amp;ldquo;do
one thing and do it well&amp;rdquo; ==&amp;gt; photo sharing. ATM I don&amp;rsquo;t know about the
team, but I would probably be very happy if I worked in a successful service
and ecosystem like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt; : of course I generalized a few things&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/thoughts-on-instagram/#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but I believe they
are not far from the truth. This was a brief overview about Instagram, there are
no right or wrong conclusions: you think what you want and use it as you wish.
Have a nice day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just bragging? Oh no. There are some artists and brands out there. They
win real money from their visibility on the $ocial network.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/thoughts-on-instagram/#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Thoughts on Instagram"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/serenity/"&gt;#serenity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Account deletion request</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/account-deletion-request/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 14:15:20 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/account-deletion-request/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There is a fact that is not usually much publicized about accounts in the web:
in general, if a given web service doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a &lt;strong&gt;delete&lt;/strong&gt; button, you can
instead request manually the deletion of your account, by e-mailing the
administration of the service. Usually the e-mail you want to contact is
localized somewhere on the &amp;lsquo;contact&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;about&amp;rsquo; page of the service, or even in
the homepage. If not, you can try to make educated guesses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:admin@example.org"&gt;admin@example.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:contact@example.org"&gt;contact@example.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:support@example.org"&gt;support@example.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the last months I occasionally deleted some of my accounts and I confirm
that this method usually works all the time. (&lt;strong&gt;Bias:&lt;/strong&gt; )Well, at least if you
subscribed to services with good admin/policies in the first place&amp;hellip; But
really, even when my account couldn&amp;rsquo;t be deleted for&amp;hellip;er&amp;hellip;bad design in the
database, I got nice replies from real people (not robots :-P (yet)). There are
a few exceptions for this. One is when it isn&amp;rsquo;t an advantage for the service to
have you gone. Example? Facebook. You can only deactivate your account; there is
no option to permanently delete it. And don&amp;rsquo;t you even try to contact
Zuckerberg&amp;hellip;other exceptions I have yet to experience. If you have any good (or
bad) experience about &lt;strong&gt;account deletion requests,&lt;/strong&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to share it
in the comments. Have a nice day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Account deletion request"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Thoughts and notes on deploying Wikimedia</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/thoughts-and-notes-on-deploying-wikimedia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 14:23:33 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>selfhosted</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/thoughts-and-notes-on-deploying-wikimedia/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Wikimedia is the most full-featured wiki software out there and powers
Wikipedia. Let me talk about what you may not know yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to deploy it on Debian. While Debian tries to set everything up for you,
pulling dependencies like Apache and MySQL, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily reflect
what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, Apache creates a new process for every connection, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t scale
(see the c10k problem). While probably the most used web server nowadays, I
prefer something more lightweight. Two good options are nginx and lighttpd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, PostgreSQL is better than MySQL. This is not something I can fully argue
about, but most people I know agree on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: if you use Debian, either you&amp;rsquo;ll struggle to get the packages and
software you want working together, or a sub-optimal solution will be deployed.
I prefer a KISS operating system. For familiarity, I chose Arch Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Be aware that some people discuss using Arch as a server, mainly for
stability reasons. The point is: choose an OS that doesn&amp;rsquo;t get in your way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="installation"&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get php: &lt;code&gt;pacman -S php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a CGI program for php. I like fastcgi: &lt;code&gt;pacman -S fcgi&lt;/code&gt; (alternative:
php-fpm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a database server. PostgreSQL: &lt;code&gt;pacman -S postgresql&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a web server. Lighttpd: &lt;code&gt;pacman -S lighttpd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get wikimedia and optional dependencies: &lt;code&gt;pacman -S wikimedia php-gd php-intl php-pgsql imagemagick&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s a matter of configuration. I advocate using &amp;ldquo;/srv/http&amp;rdquo; instead of
&amp;ldquo;/var/www&amp;rdquo; for storing web files. However, wikimedia gets installed to
&amp;ldquo;/usr/share/webapps/wikimedia&amp;rdquo;, so you have to either create a symlink or use
lighttpd&amp;rsquo;s mod_alias to create an alias to this path. I prefer the last option
so wikimedia gets placed in a specific directory—for example, &amp;ldquo;/wiki&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consult the Arch Wiki or lighttpd doc pages for configuration details. After
configuring lighttpd with fastcgi and wikimedia, configure php (enable
extensions and fix cgi path info to 1) and PostgreSQL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After everything is properly configured, start the services. Arch uses systemd:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;% systemctl enable lighttpd
% systemctl enable postgresql&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;c10k problem: &lt;a href="http://www.kegel.com/c10k.html"&gt;http://www.kegel.com/c10k.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arch Wiki — Server: &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Server"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arch Linux forum discussion: &lt;a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=162434"&gt;https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=162434&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reddit discussion:
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/archlinux/comments/1wqpdw/do_you_use_arch_for_production_servers/"&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/archlinux/comments/1wqpdw/do_you_use_arch_for_production_servers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Thoughts and notes on deploying Wikimedia"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/selfhosted/"&gt;#selfhosted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>ksnctf</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/ksnctf/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2015 21:38:13 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>security</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/ksnctf/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CTF&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://ksnctf.sweetduet.info/"&gt;http://ksnctf.sweetduet.info/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write-ups&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="https://manhhomienbienthuy.github.io/"&gt;https://manhhomienbienthuy.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: ksnctf"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/security/"&gt;#security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From orgmode to asciidoc (OR: ditching emacs)</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 14:42:16 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello people, I&amp;rsquo;m back. The portal will open in 3…2…1..&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; OK, here are some
&lt;em&gt;updates&lt;/em&gt;. After taming the beast for two long years, I&amp;rsquo;m now slowly ditching
&lt;strong&gt;emacs&lt;/strong&gt; from my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;_# archers, don't struggle yourselves!_
sudo pacman -Rnsc $(pacman -Qdt emacs)
_# *ntoo users, don't lose opportunity cost regarding precious compiling time!_
sudo emerge -vC emacs &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo emerge -avuDN @world &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo emerge --depclean -a
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs doesn&amp;rsquo;t simply go out and we are done here. No, no, no. Rehab, guys.
Org-mode was a fellow companion, now what? I even moved out of wordpress just to
blog with org files&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Orgmode&lt;/strong&gt; is the most amazing to-do / organizing /
planning / tracking tool I&amp;rsquo;ve ever used, however it is completely tied up to
emacs. The only thing we can do about that is to get all the knowledge and
&lt;strong&gt;discipline&lt;/strong&gt; that orgmode teached to us, and then move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;And I moved on.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m now slowly converting my text formatting habits to Asciidoc. It is an oldie
(2002+) thing, but people are still using it, and very well, by the way.
Asciidoc is not a replacement for markdown&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but rather a full-featured text
formatting tool — markdown is KISS. I also found a nice&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; tool to blog from an
asciidoc file directly to Wordpress; and it is called…blogpost, you are right.
It was created by the same author of asciidoc, so you can probably conclude it
is reliable. OK, goodbye for now, till next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;now you realize this was useless, since I moved back to Wordpress. But at
least I learned some Hakyll and Haskell in the process.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;neither the other way around.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;not sure if it is really nice, but if you can see this footnote, then I can
guarantee you the tool still works. &lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt; : actually, the tool works
indeed, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t play nice with footnotes.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/from-orgmode-to-asciidoc-or-ditching-emacs/#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: From orgmode to asciidoc (OR: ditching emacs)"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Games: index of</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/games-index-of/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2015 14:03:36 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>legacy</category><category>serenity</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/02/games-index-of/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am a huge fan of games in general, although nowadays I&amp;rsquo;m more of a casual
player. Today I realized I never wrote a blog post about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-networks-for-gaming"&gt;Social networks for gaming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social networks of games never really existed or worked at all. Steam is the
closest to one today, but in practice you become stuck in their platform. What
would one expect from a social network of games?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See what your friends have been playing → serendipity + you can play together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track the games you have played → gamification + organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, Kongregate satisfies those properties, although it has the same
problems as Steam: its network comprises only games on their platform. To be
successful, a potential new social network should separate metadata from
games—track only information about games, not host the games themselves.
Unfortunately, I don&amp;rsquo;t know one today, so I decided to create my own list of
games. I will track comments about my gaming styles, preferences, and games I&amp;rsquo;ve
played from now on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Games: index of"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/serenity/"&gt;#serenity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>C++ man pages</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 13:00:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today I stumbled upon across a project called &lt;code&gt;cppman&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which I believe has
a very suggestive name indeed. Manual pages for the C programming language are
almost always available on Unix systems. Don&amp;rsquo;t you remember the signature of the
&lt;code&gt;qsort&lt;/code&gt; function? No problem, a &lt;code&gt;man 3 qsort&lt;/code&gt; will refresh your memory. What
about &lt;code&gt;printf&lt;/code&gt;? What about &lt;code&gt;stdlib.h&lt;/code&gt;? &lt;strong&gt;Man&lt;/strong&gt; won&amp;rsquo;t disappoint you. However,
what about C++ man pages? I first discovered that they weren&amp;rsquo;t available by
default about three years ago. Okay, so what do I do? A simple google search
will probably lead you to Stack Overflow&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. At the aforementioned time, there
weren&amp;rsquo;t really useful answers in there. Okay, some of them pointed out to
&lt;code&gt;libstd++&lt;/code&gt; docs, but using them wasn&amp;rsquo;t much convenient. The best documentation
sources you could find were cplusplus.com and cppreference wiki&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. You can
live with these on-line references, but you will quickly get bored with them.
Now, back to &lt;code&gt;cppman&lt;/code&gt;, the boredom killer and time saver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="cppman--quick-reference"&gt;cppman — quick reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="installing-it"&gt;Installing it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re an user of Arch Linux, it is available in the AUR at the time I&amp;rsquo;m
writing this post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise, you can install it using python&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; – ya know, &lt;code&gt;pip install cppman&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter the method you choose, just make sure to add it to your
&lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="using-it"&gt;Using it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;cppman sort
cppman map&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t cry, it is real. You can optionally cache all of its man pages, but I
don&amp;rsquo;t find this strictly necessary for me. The default option (no cache)
downloads manual pages on-demand. Oh, it uses &lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt; as its default pager, so you
can search for keywords with &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;. Also, hyperlinks are everywhere, so you can
use &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;C-]&lt;/code&gt; to follow them. To go back, use &lt;code&gt;C-t&lt;/code&gt;. By the way, it is
compatible with &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt;, so if you decide to cache its man pages, you can view
them later with &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; (instead of &lt;code&gt;cppman&lt;/code&gt;). Happy &lt;del&gt;hacking&lt;/del&gt; reading!&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cppman — you don&amp;rsquo;t need to read the whole article; if you&amp;rsquo;re in a hurry,
just open the project page and forget me!&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, huh? Stack Overflow thread.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last one is &lt;strong&gt;by far&lt;/strong&gt; much better maintained.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, since when reading manual pages is a source of happiness?&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/c-man-pages/#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: C++ man pages"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Eudyptula Challenge</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 12:54:40 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update: I stopped at task 06 on February. Little seems to have stopped responding e-mails. Which is sad, because I was liking those tasks =/&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am participating in the &lt;a href="http://eudyptula-challenge.org/"&gt;Eudyptula Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, which is not something exactly new, but it is as able to get you out of your comfort zone as if it were&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It puts you into the mind of a Linux Kernel developer, where you are required to write and submit patches and to complete some tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subscribing to the challenge is a mini challenge itself&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;: you must write to &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; (the superuser behind the thing) an e-mail in plain text. This means: NO HTML. This looks like a silly requirement, but it’s the way how the (real) Linux developers work, and it is actually slightly fancier than you probably imagine. &lt;em&gt;Little&lt;/em&gt; himself recommends that the participants don&amp;rsquo;t use either the Gmail web interface or Outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to document here my own experiences with Eudyptula&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-up"&gt;Setting up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I went after was a decent and updated Linux distro; doing the challenge within a Linux rather than anything else offers a better experience. Zero effort here, as I’ve already had Arch Linux&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next: a good text editor. Wait…why not two? I am using vim to compose e-mails, and emacs to write code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s next? Oh yes…a decent &lt;code&gt;sendmail&lt;/code&gt; program. It is not mandatory to have one of those, but it eases a lot the process of writing e-mail in plain text. I grabbed &lt;code&gt;msmtp&lt;/code&gt; plus its MTA. Writing a config file for it is pretty straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now I was ready: I subscribed to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-task-01"&gt;The task #01&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours later, &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; acknowledged my e-mail and sent me the instructions for the first task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should write my first module for the Linux Kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good start. &lt;em&gt;I didn’t even know how to begin, oh no!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task was to write a module that would write ‘Hello World’ to the debug level log of the running kernel when loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I had to install some dependencies to be able to compile a couple of C programs. Actually, the &lt;code&gt;base-devel&lt;/code&gt; group from Arch already contained most of the things I would need. &lt;code&gt;linux-headers&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bc&lt;/code&gt; were also relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first module, written in C&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, looked like this in the end:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="c"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-c"&gt;#include &amp;lt;linux/init.h&amp;gt;;
#include &amp;lt;linux/kernel.h&amp;gt;;
#include &amp;lt;linux/module.h&amp;gt;;

MODULE_AUTHOR(&amp;#34;Thiago Perrotta&amp;#34;);
MODULE_DESCRIPTION(&amp;#34;A gentle Hello World module&amp;#34;);
MODULE_LICENSE(&amp;#34;GPL&amp;#34;);

static int __init hello_init(void)
{
 printk(KERN_DEBUG &amp;#34;Hello world!\n&amp;#34;);
 return 0;
}

static void __exit hello_cleanup(void)
{
 printk(KERN_DEBUG &amp;#34;Goodbye World!\n&amp;#34;);
}

module_init(hello_init);
module_exit(hello_cleanup);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t get it right in my first trial, of course. In particular, I wrote ‘Hello World’ to the INFO log level, using &lt;code&gt;KERN_INFO&lt;/code&gt;, instead of &lt;code&gt;KERN_DEBUG&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I also needed a &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt; to be able to compile it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="make"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;make&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-make"&gt;obj-m &amp;#43;= hello.o
KERNEL ?= /lib/modules/$(shell uname -r)/build

all:
 make -C $(KERNEL) M=$(PWD) modules

clean:
 make -C $(KERNEL) M=$(PWD) clean&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt; wasn&amp;rsquo;t right in my first trial, either. Another requirement of this task was that this file should provide an environment variable, as an alternative location for the build directory of the kernel, opposed to being a hard coded value. I provided one from the beginning, but the way I wrote it was slightly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this code didn&amp;rsquo;t just pop out of my head out of nothing. Although I know how to program in C, I never did kernel programming before. I had to look up for some documentation about how to write a module. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t super straightforward, because I found many documentation sources about writing modules for the Linux 2.6.x version, which is outdated now&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and the modern version of writing modules is a bit different from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I was careful not to accidentally find a solution for this task directly. Of course, some people have already done it, and they could have written something about their experiences, as I am doing right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, after writing those two files and testing that they really worked as expected, I loaded my freshly built module. And yay, a simple &lt;code&gt;dmesg&lt;/code&gt; would reveal my hello message out there. It was really cool to see it worked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="text"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-plaintext"&gt;thiago@archpad ~//01 % sudo modinfo hello.ko
filename: /home/thiago//01/hello.ko
license: GPL
description: A gentle Hello World module
author: Thiago Perrotta
depends:
vermagic: 3.17.6-1-ARCH SMP preempt mod_unload modversions&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I’ve sent everything I should to &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt;, and today I got its reply, about the second task. So, let’s go…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-have-i-learned-with-this-task"&gt;What have I learned with this task?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to write a Makefile to compile a kernel module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to execute shell commands within a Makefile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to use an environment variable within a Makefile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to write e-mails in plain text and send them with msmtp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to send attachments &lt;strong&gt;without&lt;/strong&gt; base64 encoding&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to load, unload and get information about modules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modules are so dynamic and easy to load, huh? Like USB devices. I would never imagine that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a excuse for me to write something here :-)&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pun intended.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t write this in one shot. Really. Eudi←yptull←a. &lt;strong&gt;EUDYPTULA&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distro that will conquer the &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php?title=DeveloperWiki&amp;amp;oldid=293327#Organization"&gt;moon&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which turned out to be a bot.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damn, everything will be written in C from now on. That’s what we get with kernel programming, I guess.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only lazy or paranoid Linux sysadmins will tell you otherwise 😉&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This turned out to be the hardest thing of this task, yet it wasn’t even part of it.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: The Eudyptula Challenge"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tmux: a gentle introduction</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/12/tmux-a-gentle-introduction/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2014 03:00:38 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/12/tmux-a-gentle-introduction/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of tutorials and insights about tmux on the web. This post
isn&amp;rsquo;t another tutorial. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m listing four purposes of why you should use
tmux. I&amp;rsquo;m not here to convince you to use any tool; just read and create your
own judgment about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="okay-tmux"&gt;Okay, tmux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation:&lt;/strong&gt; You should probably install and open &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; to follow this
mini tutorial. After executing &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably notice nothing fancy
happens—it just feels like opening a new terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="purpose-1-terminal-multiplexing"&gt;Purpose #1: Terminal multiplexing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tmux is a terminal multiplexer. If you are used to opening several windows of
your favorite terminal emulator (terminator, gnome-terminal, xfce4-terminal,
konsole), you should probably stop that now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prefix&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; denotes your tmux prefix key. The default is
&lt;code&gt;C-b&lt;/code&gt;, but it can be changed—for example, vim users tend to dislike this
setting because &lt;code&gt;C-b&lt;/code&gt; is frequent in vim (it scrolls one page up, like Page
Up). &lt;code&gt;C-a&lt;/code&gt; is a common alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how you open a new tab (window in tmux terminology) on tmux: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prefix&amp;gt; c&lt;/code&gt;. No mouse; no need to play with two windows. To switch between windows:
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prefix&amp;gt; n&lt;/code&gt; for next and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prefix&amp;gt; p&lt;/code&gt; for previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for multiplexing: to create a new horizontal split, use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prefix&amp;gt; &amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;. To
create a new vertical split, use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prefix&amp;gt; %&lt;/code&gt;. To switch between splits:
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;prefix&amp;gt; o&lt;/code&gt;. This subset of keystrokes is sufficient to boost your terminal
productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="purpose-2-pair-programming"&gt;Purpose #2: Pair programming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you want to share a terminal session with a friend. What is a terminal
session? Think of it as an analog to desktop sharing in the GUI world. However,
it is more than simple sharing—the observer has full control over the terminal,
just like you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, a terminal session is suitable for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pair programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote support (from a technical person)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you do? Open &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt;. Tell your friend to SSH into your machine. They run
&lt;code&gt;tmux attach-session&lt;/code&gt;. This assumes you only have one active session. That&amp;rsquo;s it.
To quit, execute &lt;code&gt;exit&lt;/code&gt; or type &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+D&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="purpose-3-highly-configurable"&gt;Purpose #3: Highly configurable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tmux is very configurable and can be scripted to do almost anything concerning
shell organization. Look at other people&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;.tmux.conf&lt;/code&gt; files, merge them, and
create your own reasonable configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="purpose-4-ideprogramming-workspace"&gt;Purpose #4: IDE/programming workspace&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tmux can be used as an &amp;ldquo;IDE&amp;rdquo; or programming workspace. This becomes really easy
with &lt;code&gt;tmuxinator&lt;/code&gt;. The idea is to center all your workflow into one place: tmux.
No need to swap windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop hitting alt-tab and using the mouse. Use tmux—but only if it would boost
your productivity. Otherwise, stick to your habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation&lt;/strong&gt;: What about GNU screen? I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it. Most sources I
read and most people I know prefer tmux, finding it more modern and powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus&lt;/strong&gt;: Detaching from a terminal, then re-attaching to it later is useful
for monitoring servers, though there are better solutions for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Tmux: a gentle introduction"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using proxy servers on Linux</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/12/using-proxy-servers-on-linux/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2014 02:48:45 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>security</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/12/using-proxy-servers-on-linux/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are some times when you need to connect your PC to an access point which
requires you to route your connections through a web proxy. No panic! It is
really simple to config your linux desktop (or server, for that matter) to do
it. You just have to modify your &lt;code&gt;http_proxy&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;https_proxy&lt;/code&gt; environment
variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;export http_proxy=http://1.2.3.4:3128
export https_proxy=http://1.2.3.4:3128
export HTTP_PROXY=http://1.2.3.4:3128
export HTTPS_PROXY=http://1.2.3.4:3128&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, just execute your favorite web browser then test your new settings.
Beware! You have to execute your web browser through the command-line, in the
same shell that you have exported those environment variables. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ export HTTP_PROXY=http://1.2.3.4:3128 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; chromium &amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting the &lt;code&gt;.desktop&lt;/code&gt; application of your web browser, for example, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t
work, unless you store those environment variables in a system wide directory
(good recommendations include &lt;code&gt;/etc/profile&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;/etc/profile.d/_&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, from my experience, this is limited in the sense that it would be the
default proxy of your system, which isn&amp;rsquo;t what you probably want &amp;ndash; the common
use case is: connect to some AP, switch to its proxy, and after a while
disconnect from it &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; throw away its proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple, isn&amp;rsquo;t it? If you want to automate this task a little more, please refer
to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Proxy"&gt;Arch Wiki&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; from
where this post was originally inspired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I needed to apply this setup in a real world situation and I can confirm
it works really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Using proxy servers on Linux"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/security/"&gt;#security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>M-x review-this-blog</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/m-x-review-this-blog/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 15:19:08 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>legacy</category><category>meta</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/m-x-review-this-blog/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dear reader, this place reached more than a year of existence, and this is a
milestone I never dreamed of. I always thought that I would only blog for a few
months. However, here I still am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always emphasize that this is a &lt;strong&gt;personal&lt;/strong&gt; blog, therefore its posts are not
necessarily optimized to please you—they are optimized to be clear, reflecting
my thoughts as precisely as possible. Yet here are almost 10k views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Views are not super important because I don&amp;rsquo;t win anything with ads (on
purpose), but they of course motivate me to continue writing here. Now, as you
are with me, I decided it would be a good idea to listen to you. There is a
Google Docs form where you can say things you like and dislike on this blog, and
also suggest future topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have some time, please respond. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: M-x review-this-blog"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/meta/"&gt;#meta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Matlab debootstrapping #1</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/matlab-debootstrapping-%231/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 21:45:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/matlab-debootstrapping-%231/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Alternative title: &amp;ldquo;Matlab, second impressions&amp;rdquo;. I am trying to learn Matlab
super fast for prototyping purposes. Fast learning isn&amp;rsquo;t my preferred style for
approaching a new programming language. However, this is necessary at the
moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: This is not a tutorial. Just annotations and notes. Information
is not necessarily correct, so consume it at your own risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="matlab-paradise"&gt;Matlab Paradise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything is optimized for matrices and vectors. Matlab means &amp;ldquo;matrix laboratory&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A number is treated as a 1x1 matrix. This is really interesting and has nice implications and syntactic sugar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matrix manipulation&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;A = [1,2,3]&lt;/code&gt; is a row vector; &lt;code&gt;B = [1;2;3]&lt;/code&gt; is a column vector; &lt;code&gt;C = [1,2;3,4]&lt;/code&gt; mixes them together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slicing&lt;/strong&gt;: Python style, but with different syntax. &lt;code&gt;1:10&lt;/code&gt; means &lt;code&gt;range(1,10)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;1:2:5&lt;/code&gt; means &lt;code&gt;range(1,5,2)&lt;/code&gt; but Matlab is inclusive (5 is present).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indexing vectors&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;A(1,2)&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;A(2,1)&lt;/code&gt;. Beware: indexes begin from 1, not zero.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance&lt;/strong&gt;: slow, slow, slow. See benchmarks on Julia&amp;rsquo;s homepage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;matlab -nodesktop&lt;/code&gt; for command-line prompt. Self-contained, and you can still browse help with &lt;code&gt;doc lu&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;help lu&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introspection #1&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;whos&lt;/code&gt;. Know everything about your variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workspace view&lt;/strong&gt;: Really nice. Save variables with &lt;code&gt;save out.mat&lt;/code&gt;. Load them with &lt;code&gt;load out.mat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some Unix goodness is available: &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ls -l&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, &lt;code&gt;mkdir&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;rmdir&lt;/code&gt; work differently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello, world!&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;fprintf('string here')&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;display('hello, world!')&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strings are enclosed with single quotes, not double. Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functions&lt;/strong&gt;: C/C++/Java style. &lt;code&gt;f(a,b,c,d,e)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some functions have more than one return value: &lt;code&gt;ret1, ret2 = f(a,b,c)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clear screen: &lt;code&gt;C-l&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;clc&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beware!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;clear&lt;/code&gt; deletes your variables. &lt;code&gt;clear var&lt;/code&gt; is more specific. &lt;code&gt;clear all&lt;/code&gt; is even more destructive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auto-completion with TAB. No &lt;code&gt;C-Space&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need help? &lt;code&gt;lu(&lt;/code&gt; then F1. Hints? &lt;code&gt;C-F1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matlab hotkeys seem optimized for emacs users. See &lt;code&gt;C-y&lt;/code&gt; (yank/paste), &lt;code&gt;C-k&lt;/code&gt; (kill/copy), &lt;code&gt;C-a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;C-e&lt;/code&gt; (navigation), &lt;code&gt;C-s&lt;/code&gt; (search), &lt;code&gt;C-_&lt;/code&gt; (undo).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;open file.m&lt;/code&gt; to open files without the fancy GUI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;delete file.m&lt;/code&gt;. Not &lt;code&gt;rm&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comments with percent sign (%). Why not hashes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a Matlab script: &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; into its directory then type &lt;code&gt;file&amp;lt;CR&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in the prompt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;version&lt;/code&gt;! R2014a == 8.3.0.x&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;C-c&lt;/code&gt; for long computations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;rand(2,2)&lt;/code&gt; if you ran out of creativity for numbers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;v = [1 2]&lt;/code&gt; equals &lt;code&gt;v = [1,2]&lt;/code&gt;. Who needs commas?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Element-wise operators are preceded with a dot. Example: &lt;code&gt;.*&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love intelligent prompts: &lt;code&gt;C-p&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;M-p&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;C-n&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;M-n&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;UP&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;DOWN&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Miss your shell? &lt;code&gt;system('echo Hello world!')&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File handling: &lt;code&gt;fid = fopen('file.txt','w'); fprintf(fid,'...'); fclose(fid);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introspection"&gt;Introspection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;which lu.m&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;which lu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;edit lu.m&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;edit lu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;help &amp;lt;command&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; spits output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;doc &amp;lt;command&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; opens help browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;whos&lt;/code&gt; shows your variables and symbols and functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;type &amp;lt;command&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Like Unix&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;cat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try double-clicking on a variable in your workspace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;path&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="internals-functions-variables-types-control-flow"&gt;Internals: Functions, variables, types, control flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sum(a), min(a), max(a), median(a), var(a), prod(a), mean(a), size(a), mode(a), std(a)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt; is 0. &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; is 1. Case sensitive!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;isvector(a), isempty(a)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not is a tilde &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt;, not &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; (C-style)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matrix indexing&lt;/strong&gt;: Column 2: &lt;code&gt;a(:,2)&lt;/code&gt;; Line 2: &lt;code&gt;a(2,:)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;inv(a)&lt;/code&gt; for inverse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;find (a &amp;lt; 3)&lt;/code&gt; filter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;2^3 == 8&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick matrix generation: &lt;code&gt;zeros, ones, eye, magic, rand&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Math: &lt;code&gt;cos(pi), sin(pi), tan(pi), tanh(pi)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More math: &lt;code&gt;rad2deg(pi) == 180, deg2rad&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;det(m), rank(m), trace(m), a,b = lu(m)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;if, elseif, else, end&lt;/code&gt;. No parenthesis required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;for k=1:10; display('hey'); end&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;switch b; case 1; display('one'); end&lt;/code&gt;. No colon after cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="symbolic-math-librarytoolbox"&gt;Symbolic math library/toolbox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;syms x y z&lt;/code&gt; shorthand for &lt;code&gt;x = sym('x')&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;x = sym('x', [2 1])&lt;/code&gt; for a symbolic column vector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;f = x + y^2&lt;/code&gt; symbolic function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;subs(f, [x y], [1 2])&lt;/code&gt; evaluates the function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;gradient(f), hessian(f), ccode(f)&lt;/code&gt; magic functions!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fancy-stuff"&gt;Fancy stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;diary on&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;diary off&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;help diary&lt;/code&gt; to record terminal sessions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Matlab debootstrapping #1"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>★ i3 window manager</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/i3-window-manager/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 02:35:49 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>bestof</category><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/i3-window-manager/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a huge fan of the &lt;a href="http://i3wm.org"&gt;i3&lt;/a&gt;tiling window manager. It was the
first &amp;lsquo;simple&amp;rsquo; window manager I tried, and it is still my favorite one. It eases
the management of your windows, is optimized for keyboard control, and maximizes
all the space you have available, thus being a nice option for laptop users. i3
is packaged for most Linux and BSD distributions. You just have to install it
through your package manager, then enjoy simplicity and agility. In this post
I&amp;rsquo;ll share a couple of configurations and tweaks I use for my day-to-day
computing and programming tasks on i3. First thing: the &lt;strong&gt;statusbar&lt;/strong&gt;. My
preferred one is &lt;a href="https://github.com/vivien/i3blocks"&gt;i3blocks&lt;/a&gt;. A statusbar
should be easy to config and tweak, and should not be bloated. Only the
information you really care about should be displayed on it. Colors are also
welcome, as they are a good design practice. Essential blocks include the
battery of your laptop, the system load, the current date and time, and whether
you are connected to the web or not. I also like to have a block which displays
my current network speed (download/upload) and another one for system memory and
swap. Optional things include volume and the currently playing song. Second
thing: the background of your desktop. You&amp;rsquo;ll rarely see it, but it is nice to
have something other than a black background fill color. &lt;strong&gt;feh&lt;/strong&gt; is the best
wallpaper setter for i3. A simple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;feh --bg-scale '/home/thiago/Pictures/wallpaper.jpg'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sets your background image, and creates a &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.fehbg&lt;/code&gt; shell script, which you
can run to reload your wallpaper later on. Third thing: a i3lock which blurs the
current view of your desktop is very nice. I like &lt;code&gt;i3lock-wrapper&lt;/code&gt; from
i3-extras repository by ashinkarov, available on
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ashinkarov/i3-extras"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. There are other interesting
things there. &lt;code&gt;j4-make-config&lt;/code&gt; is great for managing i3-themes, in the case you
dislike the default one. It is available on &lt;a href="http://www.j4tools.org/"&gt;http://www.j4tools.org/&lt;/a&gt;. Workspace
management should be simple, so I don&amp;rsquo;t use names for them. Just numbers. When
you use names, it becomes annoying when a given window is not in the proper
workspace. While you can force them to go its proper place in your i3 config
file, this process is more automatic than I need and it keeps getting in my way,
so I decided it is better not to give names to my workspaces. If you use dual
monitors, &lt;code&gt;xrandr&lt;/code&gt; is your best friend. I like to have the following aliases in
my shell rc file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;alias xrandr-t-hdmi-connect=&amp;quot;xrandr --output LVDS1 --primary --output HDMI1 --auto --left-of LVDS1&amp;quot;
alias xrandr-t-hdmi-disconnect=&amp;quot;xrandr --output HDMI1 --off&amp;quot;
alias xrandr-t-hdmi-mirror=&amp;quot;xrandr --output LVDS1 --primary --auto --output HDMI1 --auto --same-as LVDS1&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;arandr&lt;/code&gt; also helps when you need something a bit more advanced. Those set of
configs makes me happy on i3. There are several more i3 customizations you can
do, and I&amp;rsquo;ll leave a couple of references here. Other ones were already
mentioned through the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/I3"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/I3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://i3wm.org/docs/"&gt;https://i3wm.org/docs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a good window manager, the next step is to achieve a good shell
environment (urxvt + tmux + zsh). More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: i3 window manager"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/bestof/"&gt;#bestof&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Vim shortcuts everywhere</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/vim-shortcuts-everywhere/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2014 12:03:07 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>vim</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/vim-shortcuts-everywhere/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been switching my mind and workflow from emacs keybindings to vim
ones, so there is nothing better than being able to use those shortcut keys on
as many applications as possible. Currently ones I&amp;rsquo;m trying include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;emacs with evil-mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firefox with vimperator (there&amp;rsquo;s an Arch package for it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chromium with vimium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;luakit (KISS web browsing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tmux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i3 window manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit: forgot this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;zathura (PDF/PS/DJVU viewer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure there is plenty more to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Vim shortcuts everywhere"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/vim/"&gt;#vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>btrfs trouble, trouble, and troubleshooting</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/btrfs-trouble-trouble-and-troubleshooting/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 00:01:43 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/11/btrfs-trouble-trouble-and-troubleshooting/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The last weekend I lost more than &lt;strong&gt;8 hours&lt;/strong&gt; trying to recover from a serious
bug that reached the btrfs filesystem in recent days. This bug was relatively
specific: it would only affect Linux users running a specific kernel version
(3.17.1, if I recall correctly), a specific version of the btrfs-progs package,
&lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; systems with read-only snapshots — yeah, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using the snapshot
feature of the btrfs filesystem extensively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="first-symptom"&gt;First Symptom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a &lt;code&gt;pacman -Syu&lt;/code&gt;, my entire filesystem became read-only. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t save
anything. So I rebooted it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I found myself directly in the initramfs rescue prompt. I&amp;rsquo;ve always had
nightmares with this prompt. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have access to all my files until I got
rid of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few Google searches alerted me that this was a &lt;strong&gt;severe/critical&lt;/strong&gt; bug.
However, fortunately (or unfortunately&amp;hellip;), other beta and enthusiastic people
also had it. The Arch Linux bug tracker and its discussion forums contained
mentions about it. They served as an initial &amp;ldquo;what am I supposed to do now,
besides screaming?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-recovery-process"&gt;The Recovery Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had backups, but they were a few weeks old. During this process, I fell in
love with the &lt;strong&gt;grml Linux distribution&lt;/strong&gt;. It is amazing for recovery processes
and inspired the creators of Arch (the other inspiration is CRUX, which I still
haven&amp;rsquo;t tried). It&amp;rsquo;s based on Debian/testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From grml, I logged into Hexchat (an IRC client) in the #btrfs channel, and
within less than five minutes I got help and orientation from a guy who had the
same problems. He told me what I was supposed to do, and it really worked! Now I
have my system back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-it-took-8-hours"&gt;Why It Took 8+ Hours&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t that straightforward. Mainly because I was downloading several distros
and dd&amp;rsquo;ing them onto USB Flash Drives from a grml virtual machine inside the
Windows 8 desktop from my parents&amp;rsquo; house. I did this several times until I
realized (well, the #btrfs guy realized) that I needed a recent Linux kernel to
do the recovery process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Linux distribution has a recent kernel? Arch, of course. The actual
recovery process was done inside an Arch live medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grml taught me several things to expect from a recovery distribution designed
for system administrators. Unfortunately, its kernel was relatively old at the
time (it&amp;rsquo;s based on Debian, so I can&amp;rsquo;t blame it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-takeaway"&gt;The Takeaway&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although losing several hours, I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discovered a nice Linux distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was convinced (again) that IRC is still awesome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could post on the Arch forums confirming the solution I used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Had fun in the process &lt;strong&gt;(YES. I love this sysadmin thing.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moral of the story: BACKUP YOUR SYSTEMS!!!! And sleep well.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m now using ext4 on my root partition and btrfs on my home partition. This
means I can hibernate my system now — I missed that for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=188900"&gt;https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=188900&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bugs.archlinux.org/task/42563"&gt;https://bugs.archlinux.org/task/42563&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: btrfs trouble, trouble, and troubleshooting"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My last *nix setup</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/my-last-nix-setup/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 12:19:04 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/my-last-nix-setup/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve just completed my objective with this blog. Should I start a new one? After
looping through a BSD distro and dozens of Linux distributions, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally
decided to settle down and stay away from new test drives. This time should be
definitive—I really do not intend to replace my system anymore. The point is now
I have a stable configuration and a few preferences that I would like to share
with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-setup"&gt;The Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t intend this to take too long, so I&amp;rsquo;ll be brief:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filesystem&lt;/strong&gt;: btrfs instead of ext4. Snapshots are awesome, and I also can
benefit from its SSD and compression performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partition scheme&lt;/strong&gt;: split your root (/) and home (/home) partitions. Always.
Unless you&amp;rsquo;re in a hurry, or unless you do not intend to create a non-root
user. Since I&amp;rsquo;m using btrfs, I also split my 300-500MB ext4 /boot partition.
My preferred size for root is (30 ± 15)GB. /home takes up the rest. No LVM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UEFI&lt;/strong&gt;: I don&amp;rsquo;t use it now, but I would probably do that the next time I buy
a new computer. Just take care of your ESP partition and disable secure boot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bootloader&lt;/strong&gt;: syslinux! GRUB2 is way too automatic. Syslinux is simpler and
faster. If you&amp;rsquo;re in a hurry, stick to GRUB2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linux Distro&lt;/strong&gt;: Arch Linux. Period. If you&amp;rsquo;re in a hurry, use a derivative
of Arch. If you&amp;rsquo;re even more in a hurry, use a derivative of Debian or Ubuntu.
Linux Mint is my preferred choice, but Xubuntu or Lubuntu are good lightweight
options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BSD Distro&lt;/strong&gt;: FreeBSD. I love its documentation and traditional Unix
feeling. But it was the only BSD distro I&amp;rsquo;ve tested up to today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tiling window manager&lt;/strong&gt;: i3. KISS, KISS, KISS. And elegant. With i3blocks,
please.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stacked window manager&lt;/strong&gt;: Cinnamon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full-featured file manager&lt;/strong&gt;: dolphin (or nemo, but only if you are using
Cinnamon).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lightweight file manager&lt;/strong&gt;: thunar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminal/text editor&lt;/strong&gt;: vim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GUI text editor&lt;/strong&gt;: emacs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shell&lt;/strong&gt;: zsh. With grml configurations, auto-completion and syntax
highlighting. It&amp;rsquo;s perfect. Oh-my-zsh is a common alternative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminal emulator&lt;/strong&gt;: urxvt (rxvt-unicode). With tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monospaced bitmap font&lt;/strong&gt;: terminus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monospaced scalable font&lt;/strong&gt;: Source Code Pro (from Adobe).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System font&lt;/strong&gt;: either Bitter, Cantarell, Ubuntu or Droid Sans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plug-in manager for emacs&lt;/strong&gt;: el-get.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plug-in manager for vim&lt;/strong&gt;: pathogen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Display manager&lt;/strong&gt;: lightdm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the best Linux/BSD setup I&amp;rsquo;ve ever dreamed of, and I&amp;rsquo;m really happy. The
original purpose of this blog has been achieved. Through 2 years, what I most
posted here were concerns about Linux. The purpose was to share my own ignorance
and growing maturity towards this awesome subject area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now my focus turns to &lt;strong&gt;Programming languages&lt;/strong&gt;. Today I feel the same
insecurity towards programming languages that I used to feel two years ago about
Linux. I want to be very good at a few programming languages, and at least know
a couple of them (maybe 5-10). I want to be part of a programming language
community and evangelize programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog will still exist. I will probably keep posting here with the same rate
I post nowadays, but I will probably talk less about Linux and more about other
things. However, when I get into programming deeply, I might create a new space
for that purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are still reading here, thank you. I really appreciate the support of the
people that express interest in this blog. I also hope that others could learn
something during all this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: My last *nix setup"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Emacs to Vim – Chapter #2 – Philosophy</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/from-emacs-to-vim-chapter-%232-philosophy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 23:47:21 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>vim</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/from-emacs-to-vim-chapter-%232-philosophy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Previous post. Oh man, up to this point I am slightly disoriented about emacs shortcuts. It has been probably one month since I am using vim almost exclusively. I just use emacs to blog here and to use orgmode. Yes, I still know so many of Emacs shortcuts and keybindings that I can even recite them to you while I am dream. However, I am not practicing them so much as before, so they will probably fade away some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I have used emacs for two years, so I won&amp;rsquo;t forget the basic commands, terminologies, functions and shortcuts, so no problem at all. Okay, so I&amp;rsquo;ve just finished reading Practical Vim. I super encourage you to buy the book and support its author, because this was (is!) a fantastic book! I also thanks Jason Ryan, forums and wiki admin from the Arch Linux community, for recommending the book. It is one of the reasons that made me commit myself to learn (and stick to) vim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in this post I&amp;rsquo;ll talk a little about the differences between emacs and vim. This is supposed to be an informal post, with information coming out of my head on-the-fly, so don&amp;rsquo;t expect much consistency or formality here. I&amp;rsquo;ll list a couple of topics/categories and tell you what text editor I most like in each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ide-vs-text-editor"&gt;IDE vs text editor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vim is not an IDE. I&amp;rsquo;ll repeat that. &lt;strong&gt;Vim is not an IDE&lt;/strong&gt;. Vim is just a text editor. Don&amp;rsquo;t even try to make it a IDE. If you want a solid text editor to behave like an IDE, use and stick to Emacs. Emacs is not &lt;strong&gt;just&lt;/strong&gt; a text editor; it is a &lt;strong&gt;full-featured&lt;/strong&gt; text editor. Theoretically, it might be anything you want. There are no limits about the customizations you can do to extend emacs. The limit is the sky (actually, the memory of your current hardware).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer &lt;strong&gt;vim&lt;/strong&gt; here. For two years I tried to make emacs the perfect IDE. You can achieve good results with it (yeah, &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt; ones!), however, it is best when you keep it simple. I like this aspect in vim, and now I understand why almost everyone of the Arch Linux community that I know prefer vim rather than emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vim is KISS. It is kiss in text editing. For example, vim defaults are very good; I can survive without a .vimrc. However, emacs defaults are terrible (from my point of view, and considering that I know it can be better). I simply cannot use emacs for much time without my .emacs file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="shortcuts--keystrokes--chords--modal-text-editor"&gt;Shortcuts / keystrokes / chords / modal text editor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs shortcuts mostly involve pressing &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Control&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Meta&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, plus a letter or number key. Sometimes you have to do this (which I&amp;rsquo;ll call a &lt;strong&gt;chord&lt;/strong&gt;) two or three times. For example, to quit emacs you press &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;C-x C-c&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Vim shortcuts usually involve only a few chars, but you have to switch to normal mode to activate them (most of the time, at least).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, which is better? That depends. From my point of view, emacs win in respect to speed. I usually issue a command faster in emacs than in vim. However, vim commands are better to navigate through text than emacs ones, because they are well integrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, an extensive use of Emacs can lead to RSI (repetitive strain injury). Even Richard Stallman had it once. Vim commands are slightly less aggressive (in respect to the keyboard), so the health of your hands and fingers will benefit from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people also recommend the mapping of the caps lock key to &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Esc&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in vim, or to &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Control&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in Emacs. They claim that the caps lock key is not much used, so it is more useful when mapped to &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Esc&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Ctrl&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Well, I personally never accustomed myself to this convention. It has a natural problem of compatibility: every new computer you use won&amp;rsquo;t be configured this way. So I don&amp;rsquo;t find this very portable, and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to bring a .Xmodmap file everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, who wins here? &lt;strong&gt;Emacs&lt;/strong&gt;. However, remember what I&amp;rsquo;ve said: Emacs is faster, but it will hurt your fingers if you use it for prolonged hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="command-line"&gt;Command-line&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emacs&lt;/strong&gt; command line wins. Sorry vim, that&amp;rsquo;s it. Short and clear. It is even more powerful with smex, ido and icomplete. At this point I don&amp;rsquo;t know any enhancement for the vim command line, but I have to say it is pretty good also. For now, I&amp;rsquo;m only using &lt;code&gt;wildmenu&lt;/code&gt;. But emacs wins, period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="movement-of-the-cursor-through-a-buffer"&gt;Movement of the cursor through a buffer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vim&lt;/strong&gt; is better. Period. Like I&amp;rsquo;ve said before, it is very well integrated in this respect. You can switch your cursor to almost anywhere in your buffer with just a couple of keystrokes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in Emacs I am usually mechanical, and keep repeating myself. For example, if I want to go a few lines above, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably hit &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;C-u C-p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; a couple of times. In vim, currently I press &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; a few times too, but this is due to lack of practice. There are faster ways of moving in vim than I am used to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="buffer-management"&gt;Buffer management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two editors are very decent in this regard. Since I am more used to Emacs, nowadays I find easier to manage emacs buffers; however, the vim way of navigating through them is pretty decent, so I won&amp;rsquo;t declare a winner in this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="gui-graphical-user-interface"&gt;GUI (graphical user interface)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is almost impossible to use emacs for a couple of minutes if you are not using its X version. Its console version is just awful. In contrast, vim is perfect on the console, but I find gvim pretty bad (well, at least, I feel like I am editing the console when I used it: no relevant differences).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the &lt;strong&gt;emacs&lt;/strong&gt; GUI is better. It is probably even better on OS X, however I cannot confirm that right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs books will usually teach you emacs lisp. It is very hard to learn about emacs without learning what is actually happening under its hood. When you realize that everything you do in emacs is just Emacs Lisp, you really find that very beautiful. A functional language being used for the greater good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is also a problem: if you don&amp;rsquo;t care about elisp, you will probably get bored. Fast. Very fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, vim books usually teach you how vim commands are integrated with themselves and with vim itself. At least the books I&amp;rsquo;ve read up to today. This is better on a practical basis, when you want to quickly become good with it (you see, I already feel fluent in vim with just one month usage – I felt fluent in emacs only about a couple of months, and part of this reason was bad out-of-the-box defaults).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is: you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know about vimscript to actually get work done on vim. Therefore, &lt;strong&gt;vim&lt;/strong&gt; books are better in respect to being pragmatic; buuuuut &lt;strong&gt;emacs&lt;/strong&gt; books are better regarding teaching the inner workings of the editor, and how to program and extend it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="out-of-the-box-better-defaults"&gt;Out-of-the-box, better defaults&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vim. vim. vim.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ubiquity"&gt;Ubiquity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vim. vim. vim.&lt;/strong&gt; And vi. However, &amp;ldquo;micro emacses&amp;rdquo; such as mg (the program that Linus Torvalds uses) and zile are very good. But they are very basic, they are just micro text editors with emacs keystrokes; not much features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="one-line-answers"&gt;One-line answers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="color-themes--colorschemes"&gt;Color themes / colorschemes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="plug-ins-and-extensibility"&gt;Plug-ins and extensibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs is more extensible, but vim plug-ins give you less headache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="communities"&gt;Communities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more people using vim than emacs, but the emacs community is still good today. …and my creativity ran away now. Which additional topics do you believe that vim or emacs is better than its counterpart in? Comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: From Emacs to Vim – Chapter #2 – Philosophy"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/vim/"&gt;#vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How do I blog with org2blog?</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/how-do-i-blog-with-org2blog/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2014 14:26:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>meta</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/how-do-i-blog-with-org2blog/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;: Video link: &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/108656001"&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;. This is my blogging
workflow with &lt;strong&gt;Wordpress&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Emacs&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;org2blog&lt;/strong&gt;. Example markup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-plaintext"&gt;* **bold**
* _italics_
* `code`&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ sudo apt-get update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo apt-get upgrade&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="a-new-section"&gt;A new section&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text in the new section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="another-section"&gt;Another section&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text in another section. Those are usually the formatting and commands I most
use. There are others, of course, but this is usually a fast (and comfortable!)
way of writing. You should also notice that Emacs automatically break lines for
me! Now, let&amp;rsquo;s post this post. I&amp;rsquo;ll post the video link soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: How do I blog with org2blog?"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/meta/"&gt;#meta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Everyday Podcasting - #2</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/everyday-podcasting-%232/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 21:24:10 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>legacy</category><category>serenity</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/everyday-podcasting-%232/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Continuation of &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/everyday-podcasting-%231/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. Nothing fancy, really. Just to say that &lt;a href="https://www.badvoltage.org/"&gt;Bad
Voltage&lt;/a&gt; is the most awesome podcast in the planet.
Period. And goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Everyday Podcasting - #2"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/serenity/"&gt;#serenity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Compiling / Installing pacman on Ubuntu</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/compiling-/-installing-pacman-on-ubuntu/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 23:20:52 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/compiling-/-installing-pacman-on-ubuntu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;No, this is not the classic game. Here are logs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="bash"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;bash&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;git clone git://projects.archlinux.org/pacman.git
cd pacman/
./autogen.sh
./configure LIBS=&amp;#34;-lpthread -larchive&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attention here! &lt;code&gt;./configure&lt;/code&gt; without this parameter didn&amp;rsquo;t work on my machine.
The error was: &lt;code&gt;DSO missing from command line&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="bash"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;bash&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;make
sudo checkinstall&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attention here! You could simply (and näively) do a &lt;code&gt;sudo make install&lt;/code&gt;,
however, this wouldn&amp;rsquo;t create a &lt;code&gt;.deb&lt;/code&gt; package. Since we have good tools, we
should use them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you can remove pacman anytime you want with &lt;code&gt;dpkg -r pacman&lt;/code&gt;. No need for
&lt;code&gt;make uninstall&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why this post? Because of &lt;a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=187942"&gt;this forum
thread&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Compiling / Installing pacman on Ubuntu"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Emacs to Vim - Chapter #1 - Vim plug-ins</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/from-emacs-to-vim-chapter-%231-vim-plug-ins/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 01:50:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>vim</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/from-emacs-to-vim-chapter-%231-vim-plug-ins/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the continuation of the first post. As you get the feeling and overview
of &lt;strong&gt;vim&lt;/strong&gt;, the first thing you&amp;rsquo;ll probably miss as a
probable-soon-to-be-emacs-orphan (actually, not really, I&amp;rsquo;ve already told you
I&amp;rsquo;m not going to abandon emacs – for example, this post is being written within
it, with org2blog – (too many level of parenthesis, please help me!!)) are your
customizations and custom plug-ins and extensions. A couple of google searches
would bring me to projects like janus and vim bootstrap. Those look nice and I
would probably appreciate them if I were a beginner. However, as a super user –
if you read this statement as bragging, then you are probably not understanding
the purpose of this mini series –, I like to be in control of the
personalization and settings of my text editor. Right? So, I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to
control my own plug-ins. In other words: bottom-up instead of top-down. Now,
the two state-of-the-art plug-in managers you&amp;rsquo;ll find out there to manage
your vimscripts are vundle and pathogen. I began using Vundle, but after a
few hours I realized that pathogen was KISS and superior. Period. Not that
Vundle is bad. It looks (works) okay too; in this case it was simply a
matter of personal choice. The way Vundle works is as follows: your &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;
will be populated with several lines such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="vim"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;vim&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-vim"&gt;Plugin &amp;#39;tpope/vim-surround&amp;#39;
Plugin &amp;#39;username-from-github/repository-name&amp;#39;
Plugin &amp;#39;matchit&amp;#39;
Plugin &amp;#39;vimscript-name-from-vim-dot-org&amp;#39;
Plugin &amp;#39;git://www.absolute-path-to-my-site-here.com/repository-name.git&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you just have to install those plug-ins with a simple command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="vim"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;vim&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-vim"&gt;:Plugin Install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done. It is simple, yes, but I liked more the approach of &lt;strong&gt;pathogen&lt;/strong&gt;: you maintain a git repository with your plug-ins. Each new plug-in is a git submodule within your repository. Yay, this means it is super-easy to set up and share your plug-ins with other people. This is exactly what I&amp;rsquo;ve done: you can peek out my vim repository here. Now, there is one super good advantage here over emacs. The cost of adding a new plug-in is practically zero. This has two meanings, actually:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim start-up time is ridiculously fast. Even with a dozen plug-ins, I still
don&amp;rsquo;t notice it. With emacs, if I don&amp;rsquo;t run it as a daemon, it is a
nightmare: a couple of seconds (yeah, a couple of seconds is really a
nightmare, not kidding) of start-up time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t even have to touch my &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt; to add a new plug-in. I just have to
clone a new repository into my &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.vim/bundle&lt;/code&gt; folder. Period. With
emacs, I have to continuously poke my &lt;code&gt;.emacs&lt;/code&gt; file to add, remove and
constantly tweak my extensions. Yeah, I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing that for a while, and
it &lt;strong&gt;does&lt;/strong&gt; provoke a lot of stress and anxiety. You already have to tolerate
a little bit of RSI with emacs, so you don&amp;rsquo;t need more problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, don&amp;rsquo;t undermine my (our) dear Emacs! Emacs Lisp will (and will always be)
superior to vimscript. I have no doubt of this fact and therefore I won&amp;rsquo;t even
discuss it here. Emacs is much more extensible than vim. Okay, then what? You
have to find a few plug-ins, right? In Emacs, most plug-ins with decent quality
you might find will be available either on MELPA or Marmalade and, of course, on
GitHub too. In vim, it looks like the home of scripts is the vim website itself
((1) and (2)) &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; GitHub. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a central repo or website hosting
the majority of its plug-ins, as with emacs. However, there is vim-awesome,
which indexes existing ones (this concept is like the ruby toolbox, godoc.org
and Emacs paradox extension by Bruce Connor. I won&amp;rsquo;t discuss the plug-ins I&amp;rsquo;m
using right now, however here is a snapshot of my &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.vim/bundle&lt;/code&gt; directory
at the time of this post (19 plug-ins, yay):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You Complete Me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ack.vim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ag.vim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ctrlp.vim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;delimit Mate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nerdtree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;syntastic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tagbar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-airline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-bufferline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-commentary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-easytags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-fugitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-gitgutter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-misc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-sensible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-surround&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of those have an emacs equivalent. Okay, I&amp;rsquo;m stopping here for now, until the next post :) Update: next post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: From Emacs to Vim - Chapter #1 - Vim plug-ins"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/vim/"&gt;#vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Emacs to Vim - Chapter #0</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/from-emacs-to-vim-chapter-%230/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 15:55:56 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>vim</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/from-emacs-to-vim-chapter-%230/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi there. This will probably become a new mini series. I begin by quoting
Vanessa Da Mata:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;É só isso
Não tem mais jeito
Acabou, boa sorte
Não tenho o que dizer
São só palavras
E o que eu sinto
Não mudará
Tudo o que quer me dar
É demais
É pesado
Não há paz
Tudo o que quer de mim
Irreais
Expectativas
Desleais&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it
There&amp;rsquo;s no way
It&amp;rsquo;s over, good luck
I&amp;rsquo;ve nothing left to say
It&amp;rsquo;s only words
And what I feel
Won&amp;rsquo;t change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tudo o que quer me dar / Everything you want to give me
É demais / It&amp;rsquo;s too much
É pesado / It&amp;rsquo;s heavy
Não há paz / There&amp;rsquo;s no peace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upstream URL with lyrics. Now, a little bit of context. Two or three weeks ago I
began learning &lt;strong&gt;vim&lt;/strong&gt;. This is due to a lot of reasons: one of them is that vim
is actively used by a lot of members of the &lt;strong&gt;Arch Linux community&lt;/strong&gt;, and I
usually am influenced about their tastes — what doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that I will comply
with everything, it is just a matter of trying new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that I am actively learning new &lt;strong&gt;open source tools&lt;/strong&gt;, and vim
is definitely one of the most widespread and &lt;strong&gt;ubiquitous&lt;/strong&gt; ones. I don&amp;rsquo;t need to
provide statistical sources for that, do you agree? &lt;strong&gt;Vi&lt;/strong&gt; is present everywhere,
even on my Android. (Now, almost nobody uses vi anymore, however vi and vim are
too much similar that for simple and rapid tasks usually annoying differences
won&amp;rsquo;t even be noticed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that I never became 100% satisfied with &lt;strong&gt;Emacs&lt;/strong&gt;. Hey, I like
emacs very much, don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, however there were always some piece of
completeness missing in it, so this puzzle never got finished. In particular,
orgmode (an emacs task-manager-note-taker-and-everything mode) is a tool that I
felt in loved with, and thanks to it I won&amp;rsquo;t completely remove emacs from my
system; you should notice that orgmode is something very specific to emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there are some tentatives on vim implementations, as far as I read, they
are not very good (at least not compared to a vanilla, emacs orgmode). Okay,
those are sufficient for now, but there are more reasons that will reveal
themselves along the next posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://sslimgs.xkcd.com/comics/real_programmers.png" alt="Real Programmers Comic"
 loading="lazy" decoding="async" /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we should go back to the lyrics. I really love how this music is related to
emacs; in particular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tudo o que quer me dar / Everything you want to give me
É demais / It&amp;rsquo;s too much
É pesado / It&amp;rsquo;s heavy
Não há paz / There&amp;rsquo;s no peace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s is right. Emacs always was regarded to as the dinosaur, as the operating
system of your computer, as the I-want-to-rule-all-your-workstation program.
This has both its advantages and disadvantages, of course. The point with vim is
that is tries to Keep it Simple. It will &lt;strong&gt;never&lt;/strong&gt; be everything: it is only
your text editor. Nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, although people will always try to write a Twitter Client for it and
similar things, I feel it is not natural. No, &lt;strong&gt;IT IS NOT&lt;/strong&gt;!! Now, with emacs,
those things are pretty natural. It was created to be extended! (Emacs is
described as the extensible text editor.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the last two years, I&amp;rsquo;ve tested more than a hundred of add-ons and
customizable pieces and bits for it: it is so cool how a functional language
(&lt;strong&gt;Emacs Lisp&lt;/strong&gt;) can improve a text editor. 2048 game, flappymacs, twitter
client, mediawiki client, xkcd browser, RSS reader, calendar application
(built-in), calculator (built-in), mail client … Yeah, emacs is everything!
Maybe &lt;strong&gt;too much&lt;/strong&gt; for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this is the part that makes me feel a little sad: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no peace&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.
Yeah, this is a problem. If you browse through my dotfiles repository on Github,
more specifically, through its commit history, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that my &lt;code&gt;_.emacs_&lt;/code&gt; file
is one of the files that &lt;strong&gt;most&lt;/strong&gt; changed through the days. I am always editing
something of it, and I am never completely 100% satisfied with the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it is to easy to &lt;strong&gt;tweak&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;customize&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;almost every aspect&lt;/strong&gt; of
Emacs, this means it is also possible to customize some aspects that I should
probably not even be bothering to (and I should probably not touch those ones).
Now, this proved to be a problem&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="planned-topics"&gt;Planned topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROGRESS Emacs&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROGRESS introduction, motivations, and so on&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO org2blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO functional programming, REPL and Emacs Lisp&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO keybindings, keystrokes and hotkeys paradise (or nightmare)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO more org-mode goodness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO lessons and overall learned discipline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO about the awesome emacs community&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO emacs blogs and RSS out there?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO evil-mode&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO Emacs on X vs Emacs on Console&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO Books and study sources on Emacs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO Vim&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO how a emacs user feels after being introduced to a modal text editor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO keybindings and maps in different modes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO gvim vs vim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO vim community and resources?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO editing text at the speed of thought, really?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO books and study sources on vim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO Are text editors still relevant today, in a world of full-featured IDEs?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoa. I hope you might like this mini series and want to see some (or all!) of
the above topics discussed. During it (please notice this comment won&amp;rsquo;t be
repeated further on), feel free to leave out any comments about your specific
experiences about vim or emacs. Also, you are encouraged to suggest me
additional topics about my experience with emacs (and my soon-to-be-born
experience with vim too), and even choose one of the above topics to I write
about next. Until the next post! (For now, read this.) &lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2014/10/from-emacs-to-vim-chapter-%231-vim-plug-ins/" title="From Emacs to Vim – Chapter #1 – Vim plug-ins"&gt;next post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: From Emacs to Vim - Chapter #0"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/vim/"&gt;#vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My first ebuild</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/my-first-ebuild/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2014 03:24:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/my-first-ebuild/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebuilds are not evil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;em&gt;Larry, the Cow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;From now on, this will be my overlay repository: &lt;a href="https://github.com/thiagowfx/overlay"&gt;https://github.com/thiagowfx/overlay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might change its name in the future, however it will probably remain on GitHub. From my experience with this blog, I realized it would be better to leave a copy of this ebuild here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="bash"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;bash&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;# Copyright 1999-2014 Gentoo Foundation
# Distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License v2
# $Header: $
EAPI=&amp;#34;5&amp;#34;

inherit font

DESCRIPTION=&amp;#34;A font specially designed for comfortably reading on any computer or device&amp;#34;
HOMEPAGE=&amp;#34;http://www.huertatipografica.com/fonts/bitter-ht&amp;#34;
SRC_URI=&amp;#34;http://www.fontsquirrel.com/fonts/download/${PN}&amp;#34;

LICENSE=&amp;#34;OFL&amp;#34;
SLOT=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
KEYWORDS=&amp;#34;amd64 ~arm ~arm64 ~ppc ~ppc64 x86&amp;#34;
IUSE=&amp;#34;&amp;#34;
HDEPEND=&amp;#34;app-arch/unzip&amp;#34;

FONT_SUFFIX=&amp;#34;otf&amp;#34;
S=&amp;#34;${WORKDIR}&amp;#34;

src_unpack() {
 mv &amp;#34;${DISTDIR}/${A}&amp;#34; &amp;#34;${DISTDIR}/${A}.zip&amp;#34;
 unpack &amp;#34;${A}.zip&amp;#34;
}

src_install() {
 FONT_S=&amp;#34;${WORKDIR}&amp;#34; font_src_install
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;? Writing ebuilds is nice, very nice (yeah, more complex than writing PKGBUILDs, I know, but at least this complexity is justified).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit&lt;/em&gt;: Thanks Buss for pointing me out a small error (&lt;code&gt;RDEPEND&lt;/code&gt;, instead of &lt;code&gt;HDEPEND&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: My first ebuild"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cool but obscure unix tools</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/cool-but-obscure-unix-tools/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2014 15:42:06 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/cool-but-obscure-unix-tools/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;amazing&lt;/strong&gt; list! Yet another one which deserves a post just for its
usefulness. See &lt;a href="http://kkovacs.eu/cool-but-obscure-unix-tools"&gt;http://kkovacs.eu/cool-but-obscure-unix-tools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Cool but obscure unix tools"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Living on Ubuntu - Instance #1</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/living-on-ubuntu-instance-%231/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 23:24:45 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/living-on-ubuntu-instance-%231/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As stated in my last post, I&amp;rsquo;m now using Ubuntu as my main linux distro. This is temporary and might even hurt a little, however I&amp;rsquo;m willing to keep going with this goal for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I&amp;rsquo;m going to document some cleanups and tips/tricks/whatever that I find interesting and, sometimes, important too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: I am a heavily biased Arch Linux user. Anything related to it in this post is probably not a coincidence. This disclaimer won&amp;rsquo;t be repeated through other posts of this series. So, you have been warned. This is important to understand some of the motivations behind the changes I&amp;rsquo;ll list here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just one thing: one of the reasons I&amp;rsquo;m using Ubuntu right now is so I won&amp;rsquo;t spend much time customizing it. So, I am deliberately cutting this list in more than a half. There are other things that I would usually do &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; I simply won&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable the &lt;strong&gt;root&lt;/strong&gt; account – by default, the root account is disabled on
Ubuntu. This is great so newbies won&amp;rsquo;t harm the system; however, powerusers
don&amp;rsquo;t like that, this is simply annoying for them. You might do that as
follows:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ sudo passwd root&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then just enter a password for it. Now you might become a superuser by invoking
&lt;code&gt;su&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;aptitude&lt;/code&gt;. And &lt;strong&gt;never&lt;/strong&gt;, I mean &lt;strong&gt;ever****ever&lt;/strong&gt; touch &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; is evil and &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; break your system sooner or later. Top used
&lt;code&gt;aptitude&lt;/code&gt; commands are probably &lt;code&gt;aptitude install&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;aptitude upgrade&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;aptitude remove&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;aptitude search&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;-y&lt;/code&gt; flag is useful sometimes,
too. So,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ sudo apt-get install aptitude -y&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then &lt;strong&gt;forget apt-get&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;unity-tweak-tool&lt;/code&gt; then change some annoying Unity defaults. What is
annoying depends on each user taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like to create a &lt;code&gt;Ramdisk&lt;/code&gt;. How? Arch Wiki Ramdisk. This also works for
Ubuntu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the &lt;code&gt;classicmenu-indicator&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like using a clipboard manager. &lt;code&gt;clipit&lt;/code&gt; is a good choice and is well
integrated with the Unity panel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add/activate workspaces. 4 of them is (usually) okay. Use &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Alt + directional keys&lt;/code&gt; to cycle through them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Super + D&lt;/code&gt; shows the desktop. (Super is usually the key with the windows
logo).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Alt + L&lt;/code&gt; locks the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the &lt;code&gt;nautilus-open-terminal&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve your &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;. How? See here. You&amp;rsquo;ll also find my &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; there
(search for &lt;em&gt;thiagowfx&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Living on Ubuntu - Instance #1"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What is taking much space on your Linux/BSD system?</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/what-is-taking-much-space-on-your-linux/bsd-system/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 21:13:52 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/what-is-taking-much-space-on-your-linux/bsd-system/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This program is so nice that I had to create a blog post just to tell people
about it: &lt;a href="http://dev.yorhel.nl/ncdu"&gt;ncdu&lt;/a&gt;. It is the most awesome and
easiest (really easy! I would indicate it to any new Unix user as well) program
to detect which folders/files are eating too much disk space on your system.
Available for dozens of platforms. &lt;strong&gt;TL;DR &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; tutorial: just install, then
type ncdu&lt;ENTER&gt; and wait for the best (worse?).&lt;/strong&gt; See
&lt;a href="http://dev.yorhel.nl/ncdu/scr"&gt;screenshots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: What is taking much space on your Linux/BSD system?"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>All over again, shall we?</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/all-over-again-shall-we/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 00:33:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/all-over-again-shall-we/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve just switched from Arch to Ubuntu. OMG, what the hell &lt;em&gt;with me&lt;/em&gt;? To make
matters interesting, I&amp;rsquo;m using Unity (not other (non-)fancy DE/WM) &lt;strong&gt;in&lt;/strong&gt;an
underlying btrfs filesystem. First point: this change is temporary; it will
probably last just for a couple of months. In the best scenario possible, this
post would begin with a &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve just installed Ubuntu&amp;rdquo;. However, there is the &amp;ldquo;I
wiped my Arch installation&amp;rdquo; thing, just because the size of the &lt;strong&gt;SSD&lt;/strong&gt;of my
ultrabook: only 32 GB. I&amp;rsquo;ve done something similar in the past: however, in the
last time, I&amp;rsquo;ve installed Gentoo – to try it – in my &lt;strong&gt;HDD&lt;/strong&gt;. It was cool and I
learned several concepts of how a source based distro works, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t used
Gentoo during much time, precisely because I&amp;rsquo;ve installed it to my HDD. &lt;em&gt;You see
the difference?&lt;/em&gt; First notable thing: it seems like I&amp;rsquo;m always having problems
with Arch. Tell me: otherwise, why would I delete it from time to time? Well,
let&amp;rsquo;s clarify these things. The problem is exactly the opposite: I &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/strong&gt;have
&lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; problems with Arch (not today). &lt;strong&gt;And this is precisely the problem!&lt;/strong&gt;. It
feels so perfect that I feel I&amp;rsquo;m missing the point of other distros. Now, you
already know I&amp;rsquo;m an advocate of Arch, but I should tell you the following: &lt;em&gt;a
priori&lt;/em&gt; I don&amp;rsquo;t claim it to be perfect for purposes &lt;strong&gt;other than a personal
Desktop&lt;/strong&gt;. In other words, I&amp;rsquo;m not &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; an advocate of Arch for servers,
or for kids, or for your fancy friends, or for use in corporal environments, or
anything else you might come with. Arch is perfect for a personal desktop
because you are the person who knows everything about it, and you feel (and you
have) 100% control of your system, and you (later on) claim to be an expert on
this Linux thing. And all of this just because of an amazing community and good
philosophy principles and practices (and a little of work from your part).
Right? OK, so let&amp;rsquo;s forget Arch for a while – you should notice I refer to it as
&amp;ldquo;Arch Linux&amp;rdquo; just a few times –&amp;gt; it is not the &lt;strong&gt;Linux&lt;/strong&gt;thing that is great
here, &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;Arch&lt;/strong&gt; thing itself, instead! &amp;lt;– –. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s go back to
Ubuntu and some motivations behind this change. The thing is: I would try Fedora
or open SUSE at first. And I actually installed Fedora. However, I wiped it just
a few hours later; it kept freezing. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only reason for this
wiping, however: I find fedora is really annnoying in some points… Well, so I&amp;rsquo;ve
ended up on Ubuntu. Linux Mint would be an option, however I felt I should get
out of my comfort zone, so Ubuntu would be better in that sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="now-to-the-ubuntu-thing"&gt;Now, to the Ubuntu thing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like and I dislike Canonical at the same time. However, I like it more than I
dislike it. So, I find Ubuntu a pretty decent piece of software (system) for the
Desktop, it is nice. While nowadays I&amp;rsquo;m not a super fan of it (hm, I&amp;rsquo;m not even
a common/normal fan…), I don&amp;rsquo;t hate it. There are a couple of reasons why an
advanced user is not &lt;strong&gt;usually&lt;/strong&gt; (however, please notice this is not the rule;
there are exceptions!) passionated about Ubuntu – or other linux distros for
novices. I won&amp;rsquo;t talk about these reasons in this post – maybe in another one.
However, there are some goals that I want to address/complete until I get back
to Arch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="crazy-goals"&gt;Crazy goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; play with the btrfs filesystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; play with Launchpad and PPAs (bzr, etc). In particular, create some .deb
packages for Ubuntu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; play with a virtualized Arch Linux – because there is a community out
there I want to keep up with, right? Examples include but are not limited to:
ssh to a VPS, gnome-boxes, VirtualBox, docker/containers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; apt-get, apt-file and aptitude (moderably advanced) insights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; get to know vim! (Why god, why? Emacs is so nice for now…) [wq!]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; insights about the Unity shell. Customization, etc. Yeah, I&amp;rsquo;m using
Unity. No cinnamon, no i3wm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; more Ubuntu specific things I&amp;rsquo;ll discover in this process…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the next days I&amp;rsquo;ll probably talk about my experience with these goals.
&lt;em&gt;See ya&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: All over again, shall we?"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Everyday Podcasting - #1</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/everyday-podcasting-%231/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2014 15:08:59 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>legacy</category><category>serenity</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/everyday-podcasting-%231/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a huge fan of podcasts. In this post I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking a little about how I
got to know them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still remember when I first listened to a podcast. I had a Nokia E63 (Symbian
3rd Edition) smartphone, with its ~250MB of RAM and its QWERTY keyboard. Oh, it
was so nice. I owned it for more than 2 years, until it got stolen. It was
really cool to try to find &lt;code&gt;.sys&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.sysx&lt;/code&gt; apps for it, because the Ovi Store
was such a crappy thing. It had an integrated podcast manager (podcatcher).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always tried to explore almost all of the options from my devices, so I got
curious about it and searched for a few podcasts. I was a soon-to-be linux
fanboy, so I used the &amp;rsquo;linux&amp;rsquo; keyword and expected to find something. This is
the first podcast I&amp;rsquo;ve ever listened to. Period. Oh, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand much
of it—only a few words. My English listening wasn&amp;rsquo;t very good in those old days
(~September/October 2012). I still watched some TV series with English subtitles
at the time (nowadays I don&amp;rsquo;t). However, I still listened to it. I really
enjoyed those three guys talking (Mark, Seth and Chris). And I still enjoy
it—serendipity proves that searching for linux wasn&amp;rsquo;t a bad idea at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This podcast isn&amp;rsquo;t really about Linux. It&amp;rsquo;s more like &amp;ldquo;life in the context of
linux&amp;rdquo;: the three friends (four, I include myself too!) talk about their
everyday lives, happenings in their country, &lt;strong&gt;bacon&lt;/strong&gt; hahahaha—and pretty much
everything. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice way to get informed about the culture of the United
States and to get updated about the adventures of the three friends (there are
so many things they talk about, from their old devices to their family).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first episode I referred to was episode #66. Now, there are about 160
episodes. I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to almost all of them—probably skipped one or another,
but it&amp;rsquo;s definitely more than 250 hours with those guys. Pretty nice, huh? I&amp;rsquo;ll
continue this new series later, with concise tips about podcasts, and tell you
about other podcasts that I enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Everyday Podcasting - #1"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/serenity/"&gt;#serenity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Serendipity...why not?</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/serendipity...why-not/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2014 23:33:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>legacy</category><category>meta</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/serendipity...why-not/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;m switching the main language of this (we)blog from Portuguese to
English. To make this change consistent, I&amp;rsquo;ve also changed its title, from &amp;ldquo;O
que venho aprendendo&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Everyday Serendipity&amp;rdquo;. I love(d) this title. Just
thought of it today, while in the bus. It has &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; to do with me (that
doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you should brute force my passwords with this word&amp;hellip;), and I was
searching for something that would represent me since the first day I created a
post here. But I could only discover it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serendipity"&gt;The Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; about
&lt;strong&gt;serendipity&lt;/strong&gt;. Main reasons for that change of languages include but are not
limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have more visitors from outside than inside of Brazil;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the Brazilian people that I know who read this blog understand
English anyways (but the converse is not true);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After writing in English for a while, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally managed to increase my
confidence in the language and practice it more and more, so why not
continue it here?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of what I write here is usually inspired by other blogs or sources also
written in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this change looks pretty natural to me. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I won&amp;rsquo;t write in
Portuguese anymore. I might do it. Anytime. I am also thinking about doing the
same thing with my English speaking…that is, I might create videocasts in
English about a subject that I know reasonably well (such as…Emacs or Arch Linux
look like good candidates). What do you think about it? We&amp;rsquo;ll see what will
happen. Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Serendipity...why not?"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/meta/"&gt;#meta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mail from Emacs - Part #1</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/mail-from-emacs-part-%231/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2014 18:13:37 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/mail-from-emacs-part-%231/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whisper&lt;/strong&gt; : Yeah, this is probably the most crazy thing I&amp;rsquo;ve ever done (with
emacs, sure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a couple of e-mail accounts out there; this is inevitable nowadays. I
usually manage them all from a single Gmail account, with a little help of POP3
&lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; automatic e-mail forwarding (that depends on the relevance of the other
mail accounts). The point is, while I don&amp;rsquo;t have to manually check every account
– just the main one –, I still depend on the web interface of Gmail. In a
scenario like this, two-step verification with &lt;a href="https://code.google.com/p/google-authenticator/"&gt;Google
Authenticator&lt;/a&gt; is a must. No
problem, but what about mail clients? Currently I&amp;rsquo;m very happy with &lt;a href="http://www.claws-mail.org/"&gt;Claws
Mail&lt;/a&gt;; it is simple and gets the job done.
Thunderbird is not a software that I personally enjoy, but I find it great to
set up (for example) for my family, since it is GUI friendly. Now, while Claws
Mail is reasonably elegant, it is not something that I use in a daily basis. Not
even in a weekly one. I only open it up sometimes, usually when I need
(correction: &lt;strong&gt;want&lt;/strong&gt;) to send a PGP signed message. Another thing is this year
I became a reasonably active user of mailing lists: there are a couple of them
that I read weekly. Reading them from gmail is a slow process (web or android,
this doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="now-lets-get-gnus"&gt;Now, let&amp;rsquo;s get Gnus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous section was intended to point out to you my motivation do to this.
There is one more: curiosity. The hacker spirit of Linux/Emacs/(whatever) users
is really special: sometimes we try out things just for the sake of trying them
out. No strings attached, not a single reason to do them. This is divided in (at
least, I hope) two parts. This one is only a &amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo; kind of setup. I
don&amp;rsquo;t know yet how to operate Gnus properly (beyond its basics), so if you only
want the technical details, go away – nah, just wait for the next post.
&lt;a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/GnusGmail"&gt;EmacsWiki&lt;/a&gt; had all the information
I needed to setup Gnus from Gmail. Seriously, I don&amp;rsquo;t need to duplicate
everything here, just follow it. Briefly, you just have to create a
&lt;code&gt;$HOME/.gnus&lt;/code&gt; file for the configuration of Gnus (the mail client (embedded)
inside emacs we are using here) and a &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.authinfo&lt;/code&gt; for your Gmail password.
I really hope you are using two-step auth here, otherwise you&amp;rsquo;ll be storing your
default Gmail passwrod as plain-text in your filesystem. Please &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t do
that&lt;/strong&gt;. As an additional layer of security in the case your *nix box is shared
with another user, it won&amp;rsquo;t hurt if you do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;chmod 700 $HOME/.gnus
chmod 700 $HOME/.authinfo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to keep those files only available to you. Next, to make sure your e-mail is
working, do a &lt;code&gt;M-x gnus&lt;/code&gt;. You should see there your labels from gmail. Yay! Now,
do a &lt;code&gt;C-x m&lt;/code&gt; to send a new e-mail. By doing this, you&amp;rsquo;ll be creating a new
buffer with the following contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;To:
Subject:
From: (myawesomefullnamehere) &amp;lt;(myawesomeemailhere)@gmail.com&amp;gt;
--text follows this line--

--

— Thiago
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty neat, huh? It even took my signature from &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.signature&lt;/code&gt;, that I use
for Claws Mail. However, about the &amp;lsquo;From&amp;rsquo; line, I suspect it parsed the contents
of the two &lt;code&gt;user-full-name&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;user-mail-address&lt;/code&gt; variables that I have
set on my &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.emacs&lt;/code&gt; file. I just sent a sample e-mail and saw it
worked. Cool, dude!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are so many things to do / discover here. Here is a mini org list to
remind myself later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;* Sending mails
— [ ] attachments
— [ ] PGP signing
— [ ] PGP encryption
— [ ] multiple e-mails
— [ ] CCo
— [ ] Integration with other emacs features: spell-checking, auto-fill,
 etc.
— [ ] Plain text only?? What if I want to send a org or markdown mail?
 This would be super cool.
* Managing mails
— [ ] Delete one mail
— [ ] Delete several e-mails
— [ ] Searching for old e-mails (this is probably better with the gmail
 interface...)
— [ ] Change a label
— [ ] Mark mails as {un,}read
— [ ] Sync mails periodically
— [ ] Sync mails manually
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, this is okay. Until later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Mail from Emacs - Part #1"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Storing passwords as plain text...no, wait</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/storing-passwords-as-plain-text...no-wait/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2014 15:18:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>security</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/storing-passwords-as-plain-text...no-wait/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we might need to store some sensible information as plain text. By
plain text I mean using no fancy stuff or third-party programs: the information
should be easily retrievable via a terminal or a text editor. So, what we can do
in this scenario? One such option is to create a &lt;code&gt;my_secret_file.txt&lt;/code&gt; then
populate it with your important data. Of course, you&amp;rsquo;ll be saving it in your
Desktop folder, where everyone with access to your computer/account will be able
to read it, right? &lt;strong&gt;No!&lt;/strong&gt; I have to confess I once did it (with the exception
of the Desktop part…of course, a folder such as &lt;code&gt;Documents/passwords&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t
help either). Nothing too much important, but it was a password, damn. So, as we
value more our data, we find a KISS way to complete the same task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="show-me-the-codeer-the-way"&gt;Show me the code…er, the way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I&amp;rsquo;m documenting how to use Emacs + GNU PG + Org-mode to encrypt
your sensible information. &lt;strong&gt;Warning&lt;/strong&gt;: I do not recommend to store your
passwords this way, because it is annoying to keep retrieving frequent used
information from a text editor; this method should be used only when you need to
store passwords you won&amp;rsquo;t be retrieving too much. Does it looks reasonable?
Okay, so let&amp;rsquo;s proceed. Here are the requirements list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emacs 23+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Org-mode (should be shipped by default with a recent emacs, if not, access
orgmode.org)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GNU PG — I&amp;rsquo;m also assuming you already have a gpg key. If not, see my previous
posts (1), (2), for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of those are easily obtained in a Linux or *BSD machine. If you are on
Windows, Emacs can be easily installed with chocolatey, but I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about
GPG, you should try this yourself. Now, you should add something like this to
your &lt;code&gt;.emacs&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="lisp"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;lisp&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-lisp"&gt;(require &amp;#39;org-crypt)
(org-crypt-use-before-save-magic)
(setq org-tags-exclude-from-inheritance &amp;#39;(&amp;#34;crypt&amp;#34;))
(setq org-crypt-key &amp;#34;A905373C&amp;#34;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only line you should change is the last one: you should reference your GPG
Key instead of mine. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know what this means, you should read more
about OpenPGP. Now, I&amp;rsquo;m showing you the results via a mini screencast:
&lt;a href="https://asciinema.org/a/11355"&gt;https://asciinema.org/a/11355&lt;/a&gt; Notice this encrypted information could be shared
on the web; but nobody would be able to decrypt it without your private PGP key.
Just use the :crypt: tag for the entries you want to have encrypted; that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Storing passwords as plain text...no, wait"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/security/"&gt;#security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Open PGP @ Android</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/open-pgp-@-android/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 18:35:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><category>security</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/open-pgp-@-android/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered a very good free and open source e-mail application for
Android: K-9 mail; it is available both on Google Play and F-Droid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, and the main reason that led me to install it at first, was its
native integration with APG (Google Play and F-Droid), a PGP implementation for
Android. As a mini review, I got really surprised with these apps. They are both
easy to use and full of features. I&amp;rsquo;m really satisfied with them, and this post
is a quick recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe it is no surprise that I really support the practice of mail signing
with Open PGP; and you probably should do it too. By the way, if you intend to
use APG, &lt;strong&gt;DO NOT&lt;/strong&gt; copy your secret key (from, say, your computer) by using
(for example) Google Keep, or any other on-line service. You should do it
off-line, securely. I&amp;rsquo;ve used Syncthing to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Open PGP @ Android"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/security/"&gt;#security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>emacs: "No Usable Browser Found" error</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/07/emacs-no-usable-browser-found-error/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 20:20:00 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/07/emacs-no-usable-browser-found-error/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve moved from Chromium to Google Chrome on Linux. But the problem is
that emacs does not recognize it out-of-the-box. To fix this problem, you can
add the following snippet to your &lt;code&gt;.emacs:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(setq browse-url-generic-program (executable-find (getenv &amp;quot;BROWSER&amp;quot;)) browse-url-browser-function 'browse-url-generic)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This assumes you have a defined &lt;code&gt;BROWSER&lt;/code&gt; environment variable (usually auto set by your system OR somewhere in your shell startup file). This way you might change your browser later and emacs will still find the correct one. If you prefer to set your browser manually instead, you can do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(setq browse-url-generic-program (executable-find &amp;quot;google-chrome-stable&amp;quot;) browse-url-browser-function 'browse-url-generic)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always evaluate &lt;code&gt;(executable-find &amp;quot;google-chrome-stable&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; to make sure the
browser path was correctly found. Adapted from
&lt;a href="http://www.fettesps.com/emacs-resolving-the-no-usable-browser-found-error/"&gt;http://www.fettesps.com/emacs-resolving-the-no-usable-browser-found-error/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: emacs: "No Usable Browser Found" error"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>adb over Wi-Fi for adbsync</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/07/adb-over-wi-fi-for-adbsync/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2014 19:33:12 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/07/adb-over-wi-fi-for-adbsync/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Serendipity is good. I&amp;rsquo;ve just discovered one can use &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; over Wi-Fi. What
does it mean? We (well, I) don&amp;rsquo;t need anymore Android apps just to transfer
files between your computer and your device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has a common drawback, though: it is not very fast. So, if you want to
transfer 1 GB of files to your device, you better arrange an USB cable. I won&amp;rsquo;t
detail here how to do that, because a simple search with your favorite search
engine will teach you that. However, here is a nice application I&amp;rsquo;ve found so
far: to transfer (sync) files between a folder in your device and a folder in
your PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workflow is very simple: first you set up a target directory in your device
(mine is &amp;lsquo;/storage/sdcard1/adbwifi&amp;rsquo;). Now, you&amp;rsquo;ll issue a command such as
&lt;code&gt;adbsync /home/thiago/tvseries/loremipsum/&lt;/code&gt;. This will copy everything from your
&amp;rsquo;loremipsum&amp;rsquo; directory to &lt;code&gt;/storage/sdcard1/adbwifi/loremipsum&lt;/code&gt;. Sounds nice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You only have to issue this command, after enabling &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; in your device and
connecting it to your PC. That&amp;rsquo;s it. No need for cables, GUI, webapps, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll notice this &lt;code&gt;adbsync&lt;/code&gt; command doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist natively. There is an &lt;code&gt;adb sync&lt;/code&gt;, but this won&amp;rsquo;t do what you are expecting. So I created an &amp;lsquo;adbsync&amp;rsquo;
(bash) function/script and set it up as an alias. Here it is: (gist no longer
available).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: adb over Wi-Fi for adbsync"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>