<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://perrotta.dev/rss.xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Legacy on ¬ just serendipity 🍀</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/</link><description>Recent content in Legacy on ¬ just serendipity 🍀</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</managingEditor><webMaster>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</webMaster><copyright>© 2021 - 2026 Thiago Perrotta ·
[some rights reserved](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/) ·
a fork of [hugo ʕ•ᴥ•ʔ bear](https://github.com/janraasch/hugo-bearblog/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 02:51:20 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Arch Linux on macbook installation notes</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2017/02/arch-linux-on-macbook-installation-notes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 18:36:02 -0300</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2017/02/arch-linux-on-macbook-installation-notes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Imported from &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/thiagowfx/"&gt;thiagowfx&lt;/a&gt;@&amp;rsquo;s gist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arch Linux Installation Notes (Macbook, UEFI, LVM ON LUKS, swap, btrfs root and home):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create an installation disk (USB Flash Drive):
&lt;a href="http://zanshin.net/2015/02/05/arch-linux-on-a-macbook-pro-part-1-creating-a-usb-installer/"&gt;http://zanshin.net/2015/02/05/arch-linux-on-a-macbook-pro-part-1-creating-a-usb-installer/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partitioning (EFI boot partition + LVM on LUKS partition):
&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/jasonwryan/4618490"&gt;https://gist.github.com/jasonwryan/4618490&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naming conventions:
&lt;a href="http://www.pavelkogan.com/2014/05/23/luks-full-disk-encryption/"&gt;http://www.pavelkogan.com/2014/05/23/luks-full-disk-encryption/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support docs:
&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Dm-crypt/Encrypting_an_entire_system#LVM_on_LUKS"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Dm-crypt/Encrypting_an_entire_system#LVM_on_LUKS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bootloader: &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/systemd-boot"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/systemd-boot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Official Installation Guide:
&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Installation_guide"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Installation_guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="post-installation"&gt;Post-installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Mac#Arch_Linux_only"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Mac#Arch_Linux_only&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/yantis/instant-archlinux-on-mac"&gt;https://github.com/yantis/instant-archlinux-on-mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Arch Linux on macbook installation notes"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Linux goodness in your Chromebook</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2016/09/linux-goodness-in-your-chromebook/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 16:29:07 -0200</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2016/09/linux-goodness-in-your-chromebook/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.google.com.br/chromebook/"&gt;Chromebooks&lt;/a&gt; are excellent for testing
and playing with Linux userland[1] stuff. And, even better, (almost) every
change you make to it can be reset back to its factory state — even in the worst
case of completely wiping ChromeOS from your computer. As long as you don&amp;rsquo;t mess
up with its &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Firmware"&gt;firmware&lt;/a&gt;, you can do
whatever you want and still be safe. Most models are cheap, battery life is
amazing for a cheap Linux laptop (8+ hours, depending on the device and on
usage)[2], Linux support is great (well, it ships with a Linux OS, right?) —
even for most touchscreen models [citation needed] — and it is simple (as in
KISS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the previous paragraph sounded a little repetitive, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to focus
on two of my previous points here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can do whatever you want and still remain safe.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Indeed, you can
reset your chromebook to its factory state with just a few clicks — this is
still hard to do with Windows and OS X, as far as I know. I think Windows 10
is introducing a feature to ease this process, however I am not sure about it
yet. This is super important (and convenient!) for people playing with a
ChromeOS device — like me. My usual way to reset the system back to &amp;ldquo;factory
state&amp;rdquo; was, usually, to install a Linux distro with the btrfs filesystem so I
could create a snapshot upon the installation was finished, and then revert
back to it at anytime I wanted. However, this solution is a little
cumbersome. The second usual solution would be to simply use a virtual
machine, but I don&amp;rsquo;t need to reiterate that this is slow and limited in many
ways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple&lt;/strong&gt;. This is really important if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to have headaches in
the long run. For starters, simplicity is always a trade-off that involves
performance: it is hard to be simple with a core i7 CPU, so if you choose the
KISS path, you are deliberately sacrificing some of your performance. Once
you accept that, we can move forward: Chromebooks are very simple devices.
They&amp;rsquo;re almost directly comparable to a tablet with a keyboard. Sometimes
they feel like a full-featured arduino.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were some small highlights about my decision to get one. Now here&amp;rsquo;s the
good stuff:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="there-be-dragons"&gt;There be dragons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer/Warning&lt;/strong&gt;: these will potentially void the warranty of your device,
and they are only recommended if you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing. Be a good user and
research before messing up with your system. I will provide upstream links with
documentation as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/poking-around-your-chrome-os-device"&gt;Enable developer
mode&lt;/a&gt;
— it&amp;rsquo;s a must; however, it weakens the security of your device. Beware and
research! This can be totally reverted with a single keystroke (SPACE) at the
login screen that will appear in every subsequent boot of your system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/how-tos-and-troubleshooting/install-software-on-base-images"&gt;dev_install&lt;/a&gt;
— to get fdisk, python, tmux, nano, emerge (for binaries), and so on. These
are just a few developer tools, they won&amp;rsquo;t scale and you won&amp;rsquo;t get whatever
package you want in your vanilla ChromeOS, however these might help a lot with
simple tasks. For example, you can format a SD card or an USB Flash Drive
directly from ChromeOS upon running this tool — otherwise, you&amp;rsquo;d usually have
to use another computer, with another OS to do it. It uses just a little space
(~100M+ or so), and it can be totally reverted with &lt;code&gt;devinstall --uninstall&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to the &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/chromebook/answer/1086915?hl=en"&gt;beta
channel&lt;/a&gt; if you
want to be slightly more into the bleeding edge — but not too much as in the
dev channel. In fact, at the time of this post, select devices in beta channel
have support for Android apps in ChromeOS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a new shell (crosh) with Ctrl + Alt + T. The default username is
&amp;lsquo;chronos&amp;rsquo;, without any password.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User-writable locations are: /usr/local (in particular, /usr/local/bin is in
your PATH env variable out-of-the-box (echo $PATH)), /tmp and
/home/chronos/user/Downloads. There might be more, but these are enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can also insert removable media (USB flash drives, SD cards), which would
show up on /media. ChromeOS can read/write filesystems formatted as ext{2,3,4}
and FAT{,32} at least.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the basics. However, you will soon find out that you cannot do too
much with ChromeOS, even with these modifications. In this case, there are three
options, and all of them involve getting a Linux distribution in some way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(RECOMMENDED)&lt;/strong&gt; Install a Linux distro on either a SD card or an USB Flash
Drive and dual-boot from it. It is really easy to dual-boot, you just press
C-d to boot from the internal eMMC / SSD, or C-u to boot from external
storage. There&amp;rsquo;s no need to play with grub, EFI, or any (other) fancy
bootloader. If you change your mind later on, just format your SD card: there
is no need to change anything on ChromeOS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(NOT RECOMMENDED BY ME)&lt;/strong&gt; Completely wipe ChromeOS by installing another
Linux distribution on its place. Although it&amp;rsquo;s easy to revert this process
through &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/chromebook/answer/1080595"&gt;recovery
media&lt;/a&gt;, it completely
defeats the purpose of getting a Chromebook in the first place, especially
now that Android apps are starting to become available on them (for
touchscreen devices, of course).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(PROBABLY WOULDN&amp;rsquo;T RECOMMEND, BUT YOU MAY LIKE IT)&lt;/strong&gt; Install a chroot
alongside your ChromeOS, such as
&lt;a href="https://github.com/dnschneid/crouton"&gt;crouton&lt;/a&gt;. I tried it however I hated
it. It is very buggy and opinionated, somewhat similar to oh-my-zsh: both of
them promise to deliver a good framework and they&amp;rsquo;re kinda large open source
projects, however they do lots of automatic things for you, and you end up
not knowing what is happening to your system. It opposes the Arch Linux
philosophy, being user-friendly rather than user-centered. Some people like
it, I won&amp;rsquo;t argue this, it can work for them; but not for me. An alternative
would be to install a chroot manually, without the help of crouton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen the first option, installing Arch Linux ARM on my Chromebook. So
far, so good: it&amp;rsquo;s working very well. Storage is easily shared between the two
OSes (by using the SD card). There&amp;rsquo;s more to get out of my system, and I intend
to share new findings in this blog. &lt;strong&gt;In particular, the most important one: to
find an easy way (not crouton!) of running whatever Linux-compatible application
I want from within Chrome OS, without dual-booting.&lt;/strong&gt; I have a few ideas (well,
it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of creating a KISS chroot), I just want to polish them a
little more before trying them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="see-also"&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://imgur.com/BrVVyNi"&gt;Generic Chrome OS Troubleshooter Chart v0.3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t say the same for kernel stuff though. It is not trivial to install
a bootloader (such as grub) or to boot a custom kernel in a Chromebook. It&amp;rsquo;s
possible indeed, it&amp;rsquo;s just not as nice or as easy as an average PC or Mac
laptop from today, especially if you have the intention of keeping the
upstream OS (Chrome OS) in the device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People probably would cite a Macbook, a Surface Pro, or something else
similar here. For starters, did you see how much they cost, in comparison to
an average Chromebook? Such a comparison wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be fair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Linux goodness in your Chromebook"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Installing Haiku from an existing linux</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2015 17:20:19 +0000</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what8217s-haiku-in-the-first-place"&gt;What’s Haiku in the first place?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an operating system, period. What might cause a small surprise is that it is not based either on Linux or on BSD — and yet it is (probably) runnable in your modern computer/laptop!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I most like on it is that the system is integrated with the GUI, so the end user gets a nice experience. This is not so common as it sounds: most Linux distributions are simply a collection of programs and utilities put together in one place, but they are not necessarily integrated — however, &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; can integrate them. This makes all the difference between user-friendly and user-centered paradigms&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Haiku is simple, so for me this post is more a hobby than something useful that I will use in the future; however, I find that knowing about more and more about different operating systems has its own advantages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more, see &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/about"&gt;https://www.haiku-os.org/about&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="installing-haiku"&gt;Installing Haiku&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; most of those instructions come from &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/guides/installing_haiku_image_disk_partition"&gt;the Haiku installation guide&lt;/a&gt;. Also, thanks David Couzelis for kindly giving me some advice and pointing me out to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get Haiku. You can do it either from &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/get-haiku"&gt;the official download page&lt;/a&gt;, or get nightly releases from &lt;a href="http://download.haiku-os.org/nightly-images/x86_gcc2_hybrid/"&gt;the nightly builds page&lt;/a&gt;. I personally recommend the nightly releases; I first installed the latest non-nightly one, but later on I discovered that is was very old (circa 2012): it didn’t even have a package manager.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which image should you download? In this post, I am assuming we’ll install Haiku directly to a (real) disk, so I’m downloading the &lt;strong&gt;raw&lt;/strong&gt; image. Actually, the &lt;strong&gt;anyboot&lt;/strong&gt; image can also be downloaded — and this is the one you will get if you opted for a non-nightly version; however, the anyboot image will be converted to a raw one in step 3 before we proceed. So, skip the next step if you downloaded the raw image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got your anyboot image? Now, convert it to raw (run this from a bash compatible shell):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ dd if=haiku-anyboot.image of=haiku.raw bs=1M skip=$(expr $(od -j 454 -N4 -i -A n haiku-anyboot.image) / 2048)
$ dd if=/dev/zero of=haiku.raw bs=1 seek=506 count=4 conv=notrunc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (2022)&lt;/strong&gt;: These days &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; supports &lt;code&gt;status=progress&lt;/code&gt; to display the image writing progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now that we got a raw image, we are writing it directly to a disk partition. First things first: find 3GB or more of free space in your disk. Then create room for a partition in there (for example, with &lt;em&gt;fdisk&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;gparted)&lt;/em&gt;. Got it? Now create a partition in there. I’ll assume the partition is &lt;code&gt;/dev/sda42&lt;/code&gt;. Please change 42 for the appropriate number in your case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the raw image to the partition (this should be done as ROOT); &lt;strong&gt;WARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: double check the partition and the disk number, otherwise you might lose data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ dd if=haiku.raw of=/dev/sda42 bs=1M conv=notrunc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol start="6"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the installation &lt;em&gt;bootable&lt;/em&gt;: you’ll need to compile and run the &lt;em&gt;makebootabletiny&lt;/em&gt; program, which can be downloaded from &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/guides/installing_haiku_image_disk_partition"&gt;the Haiku installation guide&lt;/a&gt;. It is a simple C program, so:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;$ gcc makebootabletiny.c -o makebootabletiny
% ./makebootabletiny /dev/sda42 # this one: as ROOT&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol start="7"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make your bootloader know about Haiku. If you’re using &lt;code&gt;grub2&lt;/code&gt;z, you can add something such as the following lines to &lt;code&gt;/etc/grub.d/40_custom&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="shell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;menuentry &amp;#34;Haiku OS&amp;#34; {
 set root(hd0,42)
 chainloader &amp;#43;1
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol start="8"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then run as root: &lt;em&gt;grub-mkconfig -o /boot/grub/grub.cfg&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Done!&lt;/strong&gt; Now you should be able to boot into Haiku.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="now-what"&gt;Now what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is not a review of Haiku, so I’m stopping here. However, if I write a review about Haiku, I’ll do that from Haiku 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m just leaving this here: &lt;a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/slideshows/haiku-1"&gt;https://www.haiku-os.org/slideshows/haiku-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, Arch Linux is user-centered, which means that you’re supposed to integrate the system as you wish. If you don’t wish that then you’re screwed anyway, so go away 🙂&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/04/installing-haiku-from-an-existing-linux/#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Installing Haiku from an existing linux"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Running Ogre3d locally (without installing it)</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/running-ogre3d-locally-without-installing-it/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 00:05:25 +0000</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/running-ogre3d-locally-without-installing-it/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://thiagoperrotta.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/11056835_726102464175254_2082355176_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://thiagoperrotta.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/11056835_726102464175254_2082355176_n.jpg?w=300" alt="simple build systems, huh?"
 loading="lazy" decoding="async" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; simple build systems, huh? Hello there. In this post we will run the &amp;ldquo;Basic 1&amp;rdquo; example from the &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php"&gt;Ogre3d wiki&lt;/a&gt; without installing &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/"&gt;ogre&lt;/a&gt; in the system. For that, I&amp;rsquo;ll assume you&amp;rsquo;re using a *nix system. First things first: grab the latest ogre version. At the time of this post, it is the 1.9 release, and you can find its repository &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/sinbad/ogre/downloads"&gt;on Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; you want to download the 1.9 version using the tag download feature from Bitbucket; &lt;strong&gt;do not&lt;/strong&gt; simply download the master branch. After that, extract it, create a build directory inside its directory, cd into it, and do a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cmake .. -DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=$HOME/.lib -DOGRE_INSTALL_SAMPLES=TRUE -DOGRE_INSTALL_DOCS=TRUE -DOGRE_INSTALL_SAMPLES_SOURCE=TRUE -DCMAKE_BUILD_TYPE=Release
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty much standard cmake build. If your system is missing some of its dependencies, you will be warned and you should install them. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;make OgreDoc install
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it is a good moment to read &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/303/"&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt;. The usual difference here is that we don&amp;rsquo;t do a normal &lt;strong&gt;make install&lt;/strong&gt;. Why? Because we don&amp;rsquo;t want our stuff ending up on &lt;strong&gt;/usr/local.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead, we want it somewhere where we have full access as a normal (non-root) user &amp;ndash; in this example, &lt;strong&gt;$HOME/.lib/ogre&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="basic-1"&gt;Basic 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, head to the &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php?page=Basic&amp;#43;Tutorial&amp;#43;1"&gt;basic 1&lt;/a&gt; page of the ogre wiki and download its example. You should try to build it, but take care to change all ogre3d references from /usr/local to your new install directory ($HOME/.lib/ogre). Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s it. &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; if the &lt;em&gt;basic 1&lt;/em&gt; download doesn&amp;rsquo;t come with a CMakeLists.txt file, you can download it from &lt;a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php?page=Building&amp;#43;Your&amp;#43;Projects&amp;#43;With&amp;#43;CMake"&gt;the Ogre CMake wiki page&lt;/a&gt; (clean ogre cmake project). You can use it verbatim; just put it in the same directory as the basic 1 files &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; -- again &amp;ndash; change any references to &lt;em&gt;/usr/local&lt;/em&gt; to your new install directory. Also, copy the &lt;strong&gt;dist/&lt;/strong&gt; directory too (if it is missing from the Basic 1 project), I&amp;rsquo;ll add a small observation: in the case cmake complains about pkg-config, try adding this line to the top of your CMakeLists.txt (but after the project version):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;set(ENV{PKG_CONFIG_PATH} &amp;quot;$ENV{HOME}/.lib/ogre/lib/pkgconfig:$ENV{PKG_CONFIG_PATH}&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credits:&lt;/strong&gt; the build style I adopted here was derived from the &lt;a href="https://projects.archlinux.org/svntogit/community.git/tree/trunk/PKGBUILD?h=packages/ogre"&gt;Ogre Arch Linux package.&lt;/a&gt; Thanks Sven for your excellent packaging skills! :) &lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; in your &lt;em&gt;plugins.cfg&lt;/em&gt; , &lt;strong&gt;do not&lt;/strong&gt; use &amp;ldquo;$HOME&amp;rdquo; as your PluginFolder. This seems to cause issues when you run your ogre app. Instead, expand $HOME manually (in my case, to &amp;lsquo;/home/thiago&amp;rsquo;). This is not much portable, I know, but there must be some workaround for this I haven&amp;rsquo;t discovered yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image credit: a screenshot from the &amp;ldquo;Clean Code&amp;rdquo; software engineering book by Robert C. Martin (a good one, by the way).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Running Ogre3d locally (without installing it)"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Documented dotfiles</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/documented-dotfiles/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 01:06:31 +0000</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/03/documented-dotfiles/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I just documented my dotfiles to make them easier to understand. &lt;a href="https://github.com/thiagowfx/dotfiles"&gt;Check them out on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Documented dotfiles"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Eudyptula Challenge</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 12:54:40 +0000</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update: I stopped at task 06 on February. Little seems to have stopped responding e-mails. Which is sad, because I was liking those tasks =/&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am participating in the &lt;a href="http://eudyptula-challenge.org/"&gt;Eudyptula Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, which is not something exactly new, but it is as able to get you out of your comfort zone as if it were&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It puts you into the mind of a Linux Kernel developer, where you are required to write and submit patches and to complete some tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subscribing to the challenge is a mini challenge itself&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;: you must write to &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; (the superuser behind the thing) an e-mail in plain text. This means: NO HTML. This looks like a silly requirement, but it’s the way how the (real) Linux developers work, and it is actually slightly fancier than you probably imagine. &lt;em&gt;Little&lt;/em&gt; himself recommends that the participants don&amp;rsquo;t use either the Gmail web interface or Outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to document here my own experiences with Eudyptula&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-up"&gt;Setting up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I went after was a decent and updated Linux distro; doing the challenge within a Linux rather than anything else offers a better experience. Zero effort here, as I’ve already had Arch Linux&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next: a good text editor. Wait…why not two? I am using vim to compose e-mails, and emacs to write code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s next? Oh yes…a decent &lt;code&gt;sendmail&lt;/code&gt; program. It is not mandatory to have one of those, but it eases a lot the process of writing e-mail in plain text. I grabbed &lt;code&gt;msmtp&lt;/code&gt; plus its MTA. Writing a config file for it is pretty straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now I was ready: I subscribed to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-task-01"&gt;The task #01&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours later, &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; acknowledged my e-mail and sent me the instructions for the first task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should write my first module for the Linux Kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good start. &lt;em&gt;I didn’t even know how to begin, oh no!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task was to write a module that would write ‘Hello World’ to the debug level log of the running kernel when loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I had to install some dependencies to be able to compile a couple of C programs. Actually, the &lt;code&gt;base-devel&lt;/code&gt; group from Arch already contained most of the things I would need. &lt;code&gt;linux-headers&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bc&lt;/code&gt; were also relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first module, written in C&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, looked like this in the end:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="c"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-c"&gt;#include &amp;lt;linux/init.h&amp;gt;;
#include &amp;lt;linux/kernel.h&amp;gt;;
#include &amp;lt;linux/module.h&amp;gt;;

MODULE_AUTHOR(&amp;#34;Thiago Perrotta&amp;#34;);
MODULE_DESCRIPTION(&amp;#34;A gentle Hello World module&amp;#34;);
MODULE_LICENSE(&amp;#34;GPL&amp;#34;);

static int __init hello_init(void)
{
 printk(KERN_DEBUG &amp;#34;Hello world!\n&amp;#34;);
 return 0;
}

static void __exit hello_cleanup(void)
{
 printk(KERN_DEBUG &amp;#34;Goodbye World!\n&amp;#34;);
}

module_init(hello_init);
module_exit(hello_cleanup);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t get it right in my first trial, of course. In particular, I wrote ‘Hello World’ to the INFO log level, using &lt;code&gt;KERN_INFO&lt;/code&gt;, instead of &lt;code&gt;KERN_DEBUG&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I also needed a &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt; to be able to compile it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="make"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;make&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-make"&gt;obj-m &amp;#43;= hello.o
KERNEL ?= /lib/modules/$(shell uname -r)/build

all:
 make -C $(KERNEL) M=$(PWD) modules

clean:
 make -C $(KERNEL) M=$(PWD) clean&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt; wasn&amp;rsquo;t right in my first trial, either. Another requirement of this task was that this file should provide an environment variable, as an alternative location for the build directory of the kernel, opposed to being a hard coded value. I provided one from the beginning, but the way I wrote it was slightly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this code didn&amp;rsquo;t just pop out of my head out of nothing. Although I know how to program in C, I never did kernel programming before. I had to look up for some documentation about how to write a module. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t super straightforward, because I found many documentation sources about writing modules for the Linux 2.6.x version, which is outdated now&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and the modern version of writing modules is a bit different from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I was careful not to accidentally find a solution for this task directly. Of course, some people have already done it, and they could have written something about their experiences, as I am doing right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, after writing those two files and testing that they really worked as expected, I loaded my freshly built module. And yay, a simple &lt;code&gt;dmesg&lt;/code&gt; would reveal my hello message out there. It was really cool to see it worked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="text"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-plaintext"&gt;thiago@archpad ~//01 % sudo modinfo hello.ko
filename: /home/thiago//01/hello.ko
license: GPL
description: A gentle Hello World module
author: Thiago Perrotta
depends:
vermagic: 3.17.6-1-ARCH SMP preempt mod_unload modversions&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I’ve sent everything I should to &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt;, and today I got its reply, about the second task. So, let’s go…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-have-i-learned-with-this-task"&gt;What have I learned with this task?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to write a Makefile to compile a kernel module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to execute shell commands within a Makefile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to use an environment variable within a Makefile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to write e-mails in plain text and send them with msmtp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to send attachments &lt;strong&gt;without&lt;/strong&gt; base64 encoding&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to load, unload and get information about modules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modules are so dynamic and easy to load, huh? Like USB devices. I would never imagine that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a excuse for me to write something here :-)&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pun intended.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t write this in one shot. Really. Eudi←yptull←a. &lt;strong&gt;EUDYPTULA&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distro that will conquer the &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php?title=DeveloperWiki&amp;amp;oldid=293327#Organization"&gt;moon&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which turned out to be a bot.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damn, everything will be written in C from now on. That’s what we get with kernel programming, I guess.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only lazy or paranoid Linux sysadmins will tell you otherwise 😉&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This turned out to be the hardest thing of this task, yet it wasn’t even part of it.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/2015/01/the-eudyptula-challenge/#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: The Eudyptula Challenge"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My first ebuild</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/my-first-ebuild/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2014 03:24:00 +0000</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/09/my-first-ebuild/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebuilds are not evil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;em&gt;Larry, the Cow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;From now on, this will be my overlay repository: &lt;a href="https://github.com/thiagowfx/overlay"&gt;https://github.com/thiagowfx/overlay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might change its name in the future, however it will probably remain on GitHub. From my experience with this blog, I realized it would be better to leave a copy of this ebuild here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codeblock" data-lang="bash"&gt;
 &lt;div class="codeblock-header"&gt;
 &lt;span class="codeblock-language"&gt;bash&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;# Copyright 1999-2014 Gentoo Foundation
# Distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License v2
# $Header: $
EAPI=&amp;#34;5&amp;#34;

inherit font

DESCRIPTION=&amp;#34;A font specially designed for comfortably reading on any computer or device&amp;#34;
HOMEPAGE=&amp;#34;http://www.huertatipografica.com/fonts/bitter-ht&amp;#34;
SRC_URI=&amp;#34;http://www.fontsquirrel.com/fonts/download/${PN}&amp;#34;

LICENSE=&amp;#34;OFL&amp;#34;
SLOT=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
KEYWORDS=&amp;#34;amd64 ~arm ~arm64 ~ppc ~ppc64 x86&amp;#34;
IUSE=&amp;#34;&amp;#34;
HDEPEND=&amp;#34;app-arch/unzip&amp;#34;

FONT_SUFFIX=&amp;#34;otf&amp;#34;
S=&amp;#34;${WORKDIR}&amp;#34;

src_unpack() {
 mv &amp;#34;${DISTDIR}/${A}&amp;#34; &amp;#34;${DISTDIR}/${A}.zip&amp;#34;
 unpack &amp;#34;${A}.zip&amp;#34;
}

src_install() {
 FONT_S=&amp;#34;${WORKDIR}&amp;#34; font_src_install
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;? Writing ebuilds is nice, very nice (yeah, more complex than writing PKGBUILDs, I know, but at least this complexity is justified).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit&lt;/em&gt;: Thanks Buss for pointing me out a small error (&lt;code&gt;RDEPEND&lt;/code&gt;, instead of &lt;code&gt;HDEPEND&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: My first ebuild"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Serendipity...why not?</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/serendipity...why-not/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2014 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>legacy</category><category>meta</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/08/serendipity...why-not/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;m switching the main language of this (we)blog from Portuguese to
English. To make this change consistent, I&amp;rsquo;ve also changed its title, from &amp;ldquo;O
que venho aprendendo&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Everyday Serendipity&amp;rdquo;. I love(d) this title. Just
thought of it today, while in the bus. It has &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; to do with me (that
doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you should brute force my passwords with this word&amp;hellip;), and I was
searching for something that would represent me since the first day I created a
post here. But I could only discover it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serendipity"&gt;The Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; about
&lt;strong&gt;serendipity&lt;/strong&gt;. Main reasons for that change of languages include but are not
limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have more visitors from outside than inside of Brazil;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the Brazilian people that I know who read this blog understand
English anyways (but the converse is not true);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After writing in English for a while, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally managed to increase my
confidence in the language and practice it more and more, so why not
continue it here?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of what I write here is usually inspired by other blogs or sources also
written in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this change looks pretty natural to me. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I won&amp;rsquo;t write in
Portuguese anymore. I might do it. Anytime. I am also thinking about doing the
same thing with my English speaking…that is, I might create videocasts in
English about a subject that I know reasonably well (such as…Emacs or Arch Linux
look like good candidates). What do you think about it? We&amp;rsquo;ll see what will
happen. Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: Serendipity...why not?"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/meta/"&gt;#meta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>emacs: "No Usable Browser Found" error</title><link>https://perrotta.dev/2014/07/emacs-no-usable-browser-found-error/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 20:20:00 +0000</pubDate><author>serendipity@perrotta.dev (Thiago Perrotta)</author><category>dev</category><category>legacy</category><guid>https://perrotta.dev/2014/07/emacs-no-usable-browser-found-error/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve moved from Chromium to Google Chrome on Linux. But the problem is
that emacs does not recognize it out-of-the-box. To fix this problem, you can
add the following snippet to your &lt;code&gt;.emacs:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(setq browse-url-generic-program (executable-find (getenv &amp;quot;BROWSER&amp;quot;)) browse-url-browser-function 'browse-url-generic)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This assumes you have a defined &lt;code&gt;BROWSER&lt;/code&gt; environment variable (usually auto set by your system OR somewhere in your shell startup file). This way you might change your browser later and emacs will still find the correct one. If you prefer to set your browser manually instead, you can do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(setq browse-url-generic-program (executable-find &amp;quot;google-chrome-stable&amp;quot;) browse-url-browser-function 'browse-url-generic)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always evaluate &lt;code&gt;(executable-find &amp;quot;google-chrome-stable&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; to make sure the
browser path was correctly found. Adapted from
&lt;a href="http://www.fettesps.com/emacs-resolving-the-no-usable-browser-found-error/"&gt;http://www.fettesps.com/emacs-resolving-the-no-usable-browser-found-error/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— § —&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply via &lt;a href="mailto:serendipity@perrotta.dev?subject=Reply to: emacs: "No Usable Browser Found" error"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/dev/"&gt;#dev&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://perrotta.dev/tags/legacy/"&gt;#legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>